<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Consider Magazine</title>
    <link>http://consideronline.org/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on Consider Magazine</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy;2016 Consider Magazine</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 16 Mar 2017 19:09:48 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://consideronline.org/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Should Michigan Go Greener?</title>
      <link>http://consideronline.org/issues/2017-03-16-should-michigan-go-greener/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Mar 2017 19:09:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consideronline.org/issues/2017-03-16-should-michigan-go-greener/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;March 16, 2017
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;notable-progress-but-more-should-be-done&#34;&gt;Notable Progress, But More Should Be Done&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Siri Andrews&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Campuses across the United States are striving to be more green. On prospective student tours, statistics and facts about sustainability are thrown at visitors to try to make a college appear an even more attractive choice. With an increasing environmental awareness across the country, no one is excluded; even universities are being included in the conversation. Even so, the extent to which a university should involve itself with sustainability efforts is debated. What actions can an institution like the University of Michigan take to address environmental issues? Are the actions that are already being taken enough?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;U-M has actors who strive to create an atmosphere that encourages environmental awareness and challenges its community members to formulate sustainable solutions. As a member of the Student Sustainability Initiative, I see this firsthand. We are a student board funded by the Graham Sustainability Institute to act as a liaison between student organizations and the University to strengthen the environmental community. We are also responsible for distributing grant money to student organizations taking on innovative environmental projects. By supplying funds like the ones we distribute, as well as other grants that are available, the University demonstrates its commitment to fostering efforts to make sustainable changes by entrusting students, faculty and staff to seek out problems and find optimal solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, there are many shortcomings on U-M’s end regarding environmental action. There is a disconnect between what students are hoping to achieve in their various endeavors and those issues on which U-M takes action. U-M has an incredible amount of power. Students can try to make as much change as they’d hope, but there are certainly roadblocks. For example, I worked on a project within Net Impact, a student organization, aiming to make the Big House more sustainable. While we ended up implementing an initiative to increase recycling, there were setbacks - financial and operational - that would not have been an issue if the administration were also implementing a similar project. As a student, this was not only frustrating, but also a little disheartening. Even though the University’s president has vocalized his commitment to sustainability, at times it feels like there is far more that could be done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though I would like to see the administration take more action, I understand that there are misconceptions about the University’s actions pertaining to sustainability. Although the size of our campus gives us an incredible amount of power on some fronts, it also can be our biggest - and most expensive - obstacle. Methods, partnerships, contracts and logistics are set in place, and to rework anything costs a good amount of time and money. The external environment also presents issues, including access to renewable energy, waste management limitations and the sheer cost of some environmental initiatives. It’s incredibly easy to aim for carbon neutrality, for example, but it is incredibly difficult to execute such a complex goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How far should the University extend its reach to those who may resist it? As part of the environmental community here on campus, I’m always excited to see U-M put forth a new initiative. I understand my bias - the environment is my passion, and so of course I’m thrilled by action. However, our broader U-M community may not feel this way. For example, students have expressed discontent with “Meatless Mondays” in the dining hall, because it does not allow them to choose what they may be eating that day, despite that it helps reduce our campus’ environmental impact. Again, this is something that I struggle to understand. Even such a small initiative brings about debate about whether the University is overreaching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the University should be, and frankly needs to be, doing more. How can we claim our title of “leaders and best” if we neglect to aggressively address such a pressing issue? But, most importantly, it truly comes to down to individuals in our community and their respective actions. If each community member demands more from our school, and does as much as they can on their end, then a substantial impact can be realized. Our greater question is: How do we get every single University of Michigan community member to care and to change?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Siri is a senior in Ross minoring in Scandinavian studies and sustainability. She is currently serving as the communications and outreach chair for the Student Sustainability Initiative and is a vegan in an effort to reduce her environmental impact.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;people-and-programs-innovating-for-a-greener-future&#34;&gt;People and Programs: Innovating for a Greener Future&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Patrick Birdsong&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a student double-majoring in environment and economics, I’m privy to both the social science and quantitative arguments for protecting our natural environment. While the approach my respective degree programs take may differ in promoting the fight against climate change, the message is clear to me that we need to be doing more to protect the Earth. As a leading research university, the University of Michigan has a responsibility to allocate funds and resources towards the progression of sustainable projects. This should be done through promoting research, new programs for students, and areas of study that emphasize the protection of the environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The University of Michigan is very large, and while its size is extremely valuable in terms of the influence it can have, it poses significant organizational challenges to bringing together the ideas, research, and skills of the 80,000 people that comprise the University community. The status quo of little communication and collaboration across schools and departments has lead to a noticeable lack of cohesiveness in mission and practices among University bodies focused on the environment and sustainability. In October of 2016, the University hosted a panel to promote dialogue on the issue of addressing climate change on college campuses. I attended, and at my table, which consisted of three U of M students and two U of M provosts, we talked about this fragmented nature of the University, especially with regards to fighting climate change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, the University is taking steps to promote a more interconnected policy regarding climate change, most notably with the new School for Environment and Sustainability that will be replacing the School of Natural Resources and Environment. Although specific plans regarding the school are still in progress, according to a University press release, the new school will be organized around “disciplinary clusters and interdisciplinary sustainability themes pulling expertise from the fields of sustainability science, design, engineering, policy, the humanities and the arts.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully with the new school in place, there will be a stronger sense of unity across schools and departments as the University tries to combat climate change. Although this is not the only step the University can take to promote a more unified fight against climate change, it is surely an important one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, one of the most contentious policies regarding the University’s fight against climate change has been the debate about whether U of M should divest from fossil fuel corporations in its endowment. However, at this time, that is not realistic, and is perhaps misguided. The endowment is committed to generating funds that promote the School’s mission and practices, including research, student programs, housing, and the University’s health system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Divestment from fossil fuels is often pushed as being the best way for colleges and universities to promote the fight against climate change. While I think it is a novel idea and understand the merits of the argument to divest, it is not the University’s place to take such a political stance with something as serious as its endowment. In the two previous instances when the University divested, the investments in question (tobacco companies and South African corporations during Apartheid) were undoubtedly in violation of the University’s ethics. While fossil fuel companies certainly contribute to the degradation of the natural environment, they are also some of the most impactful entities contributing to research and design of renewable energy technology. To pull our investments from these organizations would only hinder the progression of those innovations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The place for the University to support the fight against climate change is through its people and programs, not its investments. Through research, student-led organizations, and a more cohesive mission and collaboration to fight climate change, the University can have quite a large impact. The University of Michigan should be one of the leaders in the the fight against climate change, and that can be achieved successfully through constant innovation and continued improvements to the University through its most valuable resource: its people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press release from University regarding new school: &lt;a href=&#34;http://ns.umich.edu/new/releases/24397-u-m-creates-new-sustainability-school&#34;&gt;http://ns.umich.edu/new/releases/24397-u-m-creates-new-sustainability-school&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Patrick Birdsong is a senior in LSA studying economics and the environment. He is a political junkie and spends 90 percent of his time watching/listening to CNN. Patrick is also a member of Kappa Omega Alpha, a pre-law and public policy fraternity on campus, and he has two dogs named Maize and Blue.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;student-sustainability-university-action-is-driven-by-student-initiatives&#34;&gt;Student Sustainability: University Action is Driven by Student Initiatives&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Christian Mackey &amp;amp; Jacob Grochowski&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A powerhouse research institution like the U of M, given the scale of its many buildings and operations, is not entirely green or sustainable. But we want to make it clear from the outset that we believe the University’s faculty, staff and administration are supportive in both action and attitude towards sustainability in its many forms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Forward-thinking administrators are making great changes in student services. For example, student dining has been advancing towards sustainability in a number of areas, including reducing waste and sourcing ingredients from local businesses and organic producers. The University is also generous in the financial and structural support it gives to green-focused student movements. It offers thousands of dollars to start and sustain programs through grants from the Planet Blue Sustainability Initiative Fund, and staffs professionals to support student coalitions, like the University of Michigan Sustainable Food Program. This shows the University itself is open, excited and prepared to support steps towards green sustainability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This positive attitude towards ‘going green’ is, in part, because of the student body. These relatively new resources have come into being because small groups of vocal and sustainability-minded students started projects and organizations, bargained for support from the University, and produced significant results. This demonstrates that the school is by and large ready to integrate sustainable programs on campus, especially when they are propelled by hard work from students. This partnership between the school and the students is the reason why a number of green organizations on campus exist today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Student Food Co., which operates a weekly, nonprofit grocery stand on campus, started after a class project inspired a group of students to both improve access to cheap fruits and vegetables on campus and secure sustainably grown options. The founders of the organization were some of the first to receive a five-figure grant from the University for sustainability projects, which ultimately sparked the creation of the University of Michigan Sustainable Food Program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Campus Farm is a representation of the commitment that the University has made to pursuing sustainability in education and operation, and it was made possible by persistent students. More recently, the University has provided more institutional backing for this living-learning laboratory by funding a full time staff member at the Matthaei Botanical Gardens to help steward the farm and to bring students’ ideas to fruition. To date, the Farm has produced thousands of pounds of sustainable produce, hosted classes on topics ranging from environmental justice to biodiversity, and provided hundreds of hours of volunteer opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the success of these organizations stems from student activity, a lack of student enthusiasm for mindful foodiness continues to be a barrier to doing more. Student Food Co.’s ability to source local and organic options is limited by student preferences for tropical fruit over hearty, seasonal produce like greens and root vegetables. Justifying further investment in the Campus Farm is also challenging for the University, given the relatively narrow scope of majors represented by its attendees - often environmental science, engineering, or art students. This involvement pattern is not just a problem within the organizations we represent, but broadly across sustainability groups we correspond with as well. There are some truly amazing programs in food sustainability alone here at U of M: opportunities in a student-run apiary, training in industrial food systems, and bi-weekly, city-wide food donations. Members of these organizations are passionate and serious about their work, but are simply too few in number to achieve the potential of which their organizations are capable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So comes the question, “Does the school have a responsibility to be more green?” Technically yes, but the question does not capture the scope of the issue at hand. Sustainability and environmentalism are conventions to which everyone is obliged. Being green is not a condition that the administration needs to deliver to students. Instead, it is an active movement that is in need of more attention from students on campus; In that sense, students are responsible for making the school greener.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the answer for this isn’t that everyone starts their own sustainability movement. People just need to be more cognizant of their actions. Our suggestion is this: review how you’re currently living ‘green’ and consider areas for personal improvement. Whether it’s trash, electricity use, or food choices, you will most likely find there are already students on campus who can help you work on being more sustainable. If not, know the school is looking forward to helping you learn more and share that information with others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Christian Mackey is the president of Student Food Co. He is currently a senior in LSA and will be attending the U of M School of Public Health in the Department of Nutritional Sciences beginning in Fall 2017.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jacob Grochowski is a senior in LSA studying environmental science with an emphasis on law and policy. He is a student manager at the Campus Farm and the co-president of UMSFP.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;going-greener&#34;&gt;Going Greener&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Audrey Sparschu&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When developing countries look for examples to follow, they turn to developed countries like the United States. We can claim that clean air, clean water and industry regulation are important issues, and we discipline others when they fail to comply with standards. But if we don’t employ sustainable practices ourselves, many developing nations will deem it unimportant to do those things either. In claiming ourselves to be the “leaders and best,” the University of Michigan has an immense responsibility to perform the best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have a duty to lead by example and establish precedents that guide the world in the right direction: if we let that burden fall on others, we can surely expect to make slow progress. There are more resources and talent available within this University than some nations have in an entire country, so I believe that we naturally bear an unequal part of this burden, whether or not we are happy about it. But we are extremely capable of producing results, as evidenced by environmentally-friendly practices found all over campus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the more noticeable efforts are ones that students may be familiar with: single-stream recycling bins, low-flow plumbing, a massive light bulb replacement in the Law Library, default two-sided printing on University computers, a movement to rid the campus of blue books in favor of green books, a campus-wide ban on smoking, a shift to making Blue Buses hybrid, compost bins on campus, seasonal farmer’s markets in University buildings, classes offered on topics such as the environment and sustainability, and compostable paper towels in some bathrooms on campus. These are supplemented by extensive measures implemented by Michigan Dining alone. M Dining buys seafood from sustainable wild fisheries and milk from Michigan dairy farms, lessens portions to reduce food waste, donates unused perishable goods to Food Gatherers, and composts all its waste from dining operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a biology major passionate about protecting the environment, I cannot think of a better place to have attended school for the past four years than the University of Michigan. Stereotypically one of the most liberal college campuses in the country, U-M puts a huge effort into sustainability progress and research each year. In Fiscal Year 16 alone, sustainability experts at U-M conducted $65.6 million of research. Additional statistics from 2016 show a five percent reduction in greenhouse gas emissions and a 34 percent reduction in chemical outputs onto campus below 2006 levels, which shows progress toward the University’s goals for 2025.
Furthermore, 12 percent of food purchased was supplied by local and sustainable sources and 1,100 tons of material were composted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Statistics like these make me incredibly proud to be a student at this University; yet there is always more to be done. From 2015 to 2016, the amount of waste sent from U-M to disposal facilities increased from 12,900 to 14,100 tons. While the recycling rate on campus also increased to 29 percent, more changes will obviously need to be made if the University is to meet its sustainability goal of reducing landfill waste by 44 percent by 2025.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As my senior year comes to a close, I look back fondly on the experiences this University has provided for me, and I feel confident that one I will remember the best is a class called Environmental Law and Policy. Being surrounded by undergraduate and graduate students alike who care about the future of the Earth and want to make a difference feels like the opportunity of a lifetime. It has shown me that I am not alone in my commitment to these ideals, but rather part of a whole, and we are all united by similar goals. These students are among the leaders and best - some of the world’s next lawyers, engineers, politicians, and policymakers - and they all recognize that the onus is on us to make greater change happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://reports.sustainability.umich.edu/research/&#34;&gt;[1] http://reports.sustainability.umich.edu/research/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://reports.sustainability.umich.edu/goal-progress/&#34;&gt;[2] http://reports.sustainability.umich.edu/goal-progress/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://reports.sustainability.umich.edu/goal-progress/healthy-environments/&#34;&gt;[3] http://reports.sustainability.umich.edu/goal-progress/healthy-environments/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Audrey is a senior in LSA studying biology with plans to attend law school after graduation. In her free time, she enjoys cooking, doing yoga and trying new restaurants.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Have Victors Benefitted From Career Resources?</title>
      <link>http://consideronline.org/issues/2017-02-09-have-victors-benefitted-from-career-resources/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Feb 2017 19:09:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consideronline.org/issues/2017-02-09-have-victors-benefitted-from-career-resources/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;February 9, 2017
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;cubicles-in-the-chemistry-building&#34;&gt;Cubicles in the Chemistry Building&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Liz Grabis&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Reserve Officer Training Corps seems like a mystery to most students at the University of Michigan. As Midshipmen, we are very visible around campus when we attend classes in our uniforms, but the opportunities we have are not well known. While our unit office is confined to a corner of the Chemistry Building and our officers operate within cubicles, we are provided with extensive resources. The program is unique in that our training is centered primarily around our personal and professional development. The resources we are provided guide us into the professions we are obligated to fulfill after our training in university.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Applying for the program and scholarship is similar to applying for any college, with transcripts, essays, personal information, and interests. However, it also includes an interview with an officer, a physical fitness test, and a medical qualification. Students are also welcome to participate in the program in the hopes of attaining a scholarship during their time in college.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once in the program, we are committed to a minimum service requirement of four to five years as officers in the Navy, depending on our chosen major. As a nursing major, I will serve as a Naval nurse for four years after I complete the NROTC program and obtain my nursing degree. Each week, we have to attend morning workouts, our naval science classes, and our Leadership Lab. We are also required to participate in summer cruises that consist of real life training in the fleet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything that we do throughout our time is college is designed to help us achieve our goals of commissioning as naval officers. The mission statement of NROTC states: “The NROTC Program was established&amp;hellip;in order to commission college graduates as naval officers who possess a basic professional background, are motivated toward careers in the naval service, and have a potential for future development in mind and character so as to assume the highest responsibilities of command, citizenship and government.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In practice, this mission statement guides the resources that are available for us. Because we have distinct and concrete career goals, the officers in our unit are motivated towards helping us to succeed. All of the officers teach our naval science classes, which include lessons on naval history, customs, traditions, leadership and management, navigation, warfare, operations, and ethics. They are present in our Leadership Lab, which is used to develop our leadership abilities and expose us to possible specialties and opportunities for our futures. We are all also assigned to an officer who serves as our academic advisor and meets with us throughout our semesters to establish our goals and mark our progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The structure of our battalion also serves as a resource for our career development. Each semester, we are assigned to billets, or jobs, to give us practice with various skills and leadership positions. For example, this semester I am in charge of recruiting, which means that I assist students interested in joining our unit. Our billets operate within a chain of command, which gives us the knowledge needed to communicate within a unit when we commission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we near commissioning, the officers in our unit again have a large influence over our futures. As a nurse option, I already know which speciality area I will enter. However, other Midshipman have a variety of communities they could enter, including surface warfare, submarines, aviation, and SEAL teams. Some of these communities require special tests and interviews, for which the officers prepare us in our training. They are dedicated to helping us select and prepare for the naval career we choose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from all of the training that I receive in NROTC, Michigan’s School of Nursing also has very specialized academic programs. There are career fairs throughout the year, special lectures to orient us to various opportunities within our major, and our clinical experiences which expose us to the hands-on work of nurses in hospitals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the two programs are completely separate, I have two large support systems teeming with resources for me and my career development. I am always surrounded by people with the same career goals, whether nursing or the Navy, who serve as my last, but perhaps most important, resource.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Liz Grabis is a second year student in the School of Nursing and the Naval Reserve Officer Training Corps (NROTC). She enjoys kayaking, reading on the beaches of North Carolina, and visiting her home state of Maryland.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;from-michigan-to-disney&#34;&gt;From Michigan to Disney&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Monika Paliwoda&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hi! My name is Monika, and I am sophomore currently away at a co-op, an internship for a semester, with Walt Disney World’s Industrial Engineering Department’s Food and Beverage team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are an engineer with a Michigan email account, you have probably already received a plethora of emails about career fairs, information sessions, career tracks, and more. My biggest piece of advice is to read them all! Reading your emails is the first step to navigating the big, scary (don’t worry it’s not that scary) world of recruiting. The University of Michigan, especially the College of Engineering, has so many resources for finding a job, and coming into college. I hope my insight on Emerging Wolverines, career fairs, information sessions, career track emails, and eventually landing my dream internship help you navigate the job hunt world!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a freshman, I participated in Emerging Wolverines. Emerging Wolverines is a five week, small group experience that helps identify potential majors that are right for you. Even though I knew I wanted to study Industrial and Operations Engineering (IOE), I decided to participate to explore my strengths and how my personality and goals could align with other majors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within the first few weeks of school, the Society of Women Engineers (SWE) and Tau Beta Pi (TBP) hold a two-day Career Fair. Almost every building, even the far FXB, has companies lined up waiting to speak to students. Even if you are an underclassman, go. Talk to companies, get your name out there, or even just practice putting on a suit and waiting to speak to a recruiter. I recommend researching companies in advance online so that you know which day and where the companies are at the career fair. You can also see what positions and what majors they are looking for. This last part is especially important because you do not want to wait twenty minutes just to have a recruiter give you back your resume because their operations recruiter is not there that day. That being said, don’t be afraid to quickly take out your phone and do some research on a company, and then go up and talk to them. I received interview offers from companies that I knew nothing about until the five minutes before I went to talk to them!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The IOE department also has a career fair.  This takes place within the week of the SWE/TBP career fair and was an amazing opportunity to talk to companies that were specifically looking for me. The lines are usually fairly short and you get more face time with the recruiter. Go to this even just to see what companies are in your field, and what kind of jobs they offer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Career fairs are a great way to leave your mark on a recruiter, and information sessions are a great way for a company to leave a mark on you. The College of Engineering sends out weekly and daily emails about events going on on campus. Read those emails! (Have I stressed that enough?) As a freshman, I attended the information sessions for the companies I was interested in or wanted to learn more about. That knowledge of what they were looking for gave me more confidence now as a sophomore to talk to those companies at career fair.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I have an interest in consulting, so through the Career Center, I signed up for the Consulting Career Track. Every month, I get emails about case prep techniques, recruiting schedules, and more. Anyone can sign up for these, and there are a variety of tracks ranging from business to medical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Disney, I attended both the information session and the IOE Career Fair. At the Disney Information Session, the recruiter talked about the company, skills required to apply, and he even gave example case interview questions. With this in mind, the next day at the IOE Career Fair, I was able to tailor my elevator pitch to points he talked about at the information session. The co-op application itself was online, and I received a call for an interview a few weeks later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Monika Paliwoda is a sophomore studying industrial and operations engineering.  This semester, she is interning as an industrial engineer with Walt Disney World in Orlando, supporting Food and Beverage. On campus, Monika is the secretary for the Michigan Polish Student Association, a member of the Michigan Business Club and Society of Women Engineers. She also participated in the Petrovich Emerging Leadership Experience (PELE).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-glass-ceiling-of-the-audition-room&#34;&gt;The Glass Ceiling of the Audition Room&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tiffany W. and Liliana T.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Theatre has often had a reputation of challenging a norm, and nowhere is this more true than on college campuses, where young thespians are encouraged to make art that expresses their opinions, political, social or otherwise. Yet for whatever reason, this mindset of intrepidity often does not extend to race. It appears to be an all-inclusive art form, but in the casting room there is often pressure to cast the white majority. We’ve all read about #OscarsSoWhite. But while Chris Rock could constantly make jabs at the Academy for the lack of African Americans nominated for awards, other minorities were left without a voice. Non-black people of color are the minority within the minority, those forgotten even when race is the topic of conversation, and experience their own differing forms of discrimination. This is not limited to Hollywood: even as actors are in training at university, actors of color are passed over in casting for various reasons, and deprived of the career resources to hone their craft that would better prepare them for the professional world of theatre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While not overt, the problem is apparent. In casting calls, there will be no mention of race. Yet, despite a show might be marketed as “all-American,” you can be pretty sure that the cast will be almost entirely white, regardless of the diversity present in the audition room. A black actor might fit into the “American” mold, but it takes a daring director to cast an actor of any other ethnicity. The problem therein lies in choosing shows that speak to the white American experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet even when other ethnicities are encouraged with the promise of roles for “actors of color,” these plays often only require black actors, and speak only to the African-American experience - creating a double-standard. Black actors are given racially-specific roles that they can play with little to no guilt of appropriation. Other actors of color don’t often have that option. If there is a call for ‘Latinx’ actors, anyone who passes for Latinx with a bit of makeup is welcome to audition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is frustrating for an actor of color to suffer such a double-standard without any real voice or representation. Boards of collegiate theatres feel it is enough to do an ‘African American’ play, or a play that ‘celebrates diversity.’ But by limiting actors’ chances to these specific plays, they perpetuate the idea that actors of color must be cast for only racial reasons. Setting one show of five aside for these actors is patronizing and divisive. Far more inclusive and useful to actors in training is choosing productions that are racially ambiguous, where all actors of any race can work together side by side. After all, in an education setting, all students should have access to all options. Collegiate theatre should be about training young actors, and this training can only be gained through engaging in a production process. When schools pick shows that cannot provide this type of training to all ethnicities, they cannot hope to provide an inclusive educational and pre-professional experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Casting can and should be colorblind when a production is part of a student’s education. Proponents of dominantly white casts have argued that when characters are related (it is rare to find a play where there are no relatives present), it is not believable for the family to be of different races. But theatre is about suspension of disbelief - if you are able to believe that Peter Pan is flying, is it so unbelievable that a black woman can have a white father? Families on stage do not all have to be the same race, and the University of Michigan has proven this in multiple recent shows. The shows were well received, regardless of the lack of genetic integrity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course subtle prejudice still exists in casting rooms across the country. Nonetheless, there is a reason why students spend thousands of dollars every year instead of immediately diving into the professional world: for the sake of training that prepares them for a career in theatre. All students are paying this cost - white, black, or otherwise. Casting protocol that pursues the “white all-American” aesthetic, or that specifies only certain races while others remain a matter of “makeup will do the trick,” is neglectful; students of color are then deprived of the opportunity to develop skills in an educational setting, and enter the professional world without the same experience as their peers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tiffany W. and Liliana T. are students in the School of Music, Theatre and Dance at the University of Michigan.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;discrepancies-from-across-the-pond&#34;&gt;Discrepancies from across the pond&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kirsty McInnes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While getting ready to apply for my first internship, I did what many of us do: I sent my resume to my dad and asked for his feedback. I’ve always found it useful to take others’ feedback on my writing with a grain of salt, but when I received an email back from my dad saying: “Looks good, just a few grammatical errors,” I figured it wasn&amp;rsquo;t entirely true. I had been looking for some real feedback, most of which he usually gave me, so I got to thinking about why, all of a sudden, I wasn’t getting the assistance that I was used to.
My family and I moved to the United States from Basildon, United Kingdom, a city about an hour east of London, in 2003. While I’ve been stateside for most of my life, my parents’ way of life still closely resembles that of someone living in the U.K. Maybe I should have seen the slight issue of my parents being foreign coming; my dad had admitted to me that he’d only seen a resume from the United States a handful of times. I have always been aware of most of the cultural differences between the U.S. and U.K., but it wasn’t until recently that I started to realize some differences related to career application expectations may affect me more than the correct way to pronounce “poem.”
Don’t get me wrong, there aren’t that many differences in searching for jobs between here and the U.K. However, for small things such as resume-building as well as for larger things such as degrees and how much they matter when applying for a jobs, the two countries do differ slightly.
 Resumes in the U.K. are actually called CVs, which stands for Curriculum Vitae, and although they convey very similar things as resumes in the U.S. do, they can differ structurally. For example, in a CV, dates are usually listed on the left. This may seem like a minor detail, but this slight change would create a very different flow to my resume. Also, in the U.K., when you receive your degree, it comes with a corresponding “honour”; a first class, upper second class, lower second class, or third class honour. These honours actually play a large role in the types of jobs and programs you are eligible to enter after graduating from university. So trying to explain to my parents that a student with all C’s or a student with all A’s will essentially receive the same degree was somewhat difficult. These disparities led me to turn to the often-criticized but highly underutilized University Career Center.
  While I had heard some complaints about the Career Center, such as it is impersonal and generally unhelpful, I decided to give it a shot. My first encounter with the Center was attending an “Immersion,” an event that allows you to get a feel for a certain company by touring their offices and meeting with employees. The Immersion was an (free!) enlightening opportunity that showed me what a regular day at an office looks like, as well as broadened my knowledge about what types of jobs a Comm. major can pursue. There was also an opportunity at the Immersion to network with UM alumni and to gain information from an intern manager about the company’s intern program and how to apply. For me, the experience was very important; picking a career path was something that neither my parents, nor anyone really, could help me with.
  Attending the Immersion was also why I needed my first real resume; I wanted to apply to the company I had toured. I decided to use the Career Center for this purpose as well and, for me, it paid off. After talking to a peer advisor for just 15 minutes, she had gone through my resume line by line and provided much more in-depth feedback than “looks good.” She was able to tell me that dates on your resume should be on the righthand side, but also helped me prioritize which of my past experiences I should focus on most and what to leave out entirely (A.K.A. everything from high school). She went over small details as well, down to whether I should use the words “participated” or “assisted.”
  Even though the path that lead me to the Career Center stemmed from my parents being from another country, I think that any route one takes will lead them to having a beneficial experience. I plan on taking full advantage of all the opportunities in the Career Center in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kirsty McInnes is a current sophomore at the University of Michigan studying communications and planning to minor in writing. She is an associate editor of Consider Magazine and spends most of her free time binge-watching T.V. and drinking coffee.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Are Michigan&#39;s Entrepreneurs the Leaders and Best?</title>
      <link>http://consideronline.org/issues/2017-01-12-are-michigans-entrepreneurs-the-leaders-and-best/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jan 2017 19:09:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consideronline.org/issues/2017-01-12-are-michigans-entrepreneurs-the-leaders-and-best/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;January 12, 2017
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;igniting-entrepreneurship-on-michigan-s-campus&#34;&gt;Igniting Entrepreneurship on Michigan&amp;rsquo;s Campus&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ilan Siegel&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The University of Michigan has invested countless hours and millions of dollars to build the number three ranked entrepreneurial program in the country. Yet our ability to educate successful entrepreneurs is still in infancy stages. Why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The term entrepreneurship is fluid: it changes daily and has 101 different definitions depending on who you ask and what day of the week it is. It&amp;rsquo;s hard to pinpoint exactly what entrepreneurship is, and because of this, anyone can claim to be an entrepreneur. Tom Frank, Director of the Center for Entrepreneurship, recently told me that his biggest issue with entrepreneurship education across the country is that faculty will teach “entrepreneurship” when they have no qualifications or experience to do so. Would we allow a medical professor to teach neurosurgery if he or she had never operated on a brain before? Can we trust a political science professor to explain the intricacies of polling data without experience or without a PhD in political science?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One learns the qualities of entrepreneurship through experience. Failure, success and hours and hours of focus on a singular vision shape true entrepreneurs. As President of MPowered, I personally define entrepreneurship as the ability to create something out of nothing. A successful entrepreneur begins with a seed of an idea and navigates through a tumultuous and ever-changing ecosystem to develop that idea into a reality. Along the way, she must impassion her colleagues, friends and potential investors to truly believe in her idea and the underlying principles that drive her to success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Creating a successful company takes years of work and requires sacrifices in almost every sector of one&amp;rsquo;s life. 100-hour work weeks are the norm. Yet, students expect to be able to create a company while also balancing school, social lives and other student organizations. On top of that, every single student at the University of Michigan is still developing his or her social skills, time management skills and learning how to manage personal finances. Is it feasible to add developing networking skills and how to manage company finances?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is extremely difficult to incentivize qualified entrepreneurs to leave the bubble that is Silicon Valley, Silicon Alley or Silicon Beach to come to Ann Arbor to teach entrepreneurial skills. Many times this issue is exacerbated by the fact that credibly defining entrepreneurship with the same level of substance as a field like neuroscience or political science is extremely challenging. It is a ‘Catch 22’. Recruiting top entrepreneurs is challenging because many do not know what skills they can teach due to the lack of a clear definition. But at the same time, this definition cannot be developed because there are not enough qualified individuals teaching entrepreneurship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, Michigan’s entrepreneurial community is siloed. Given the diverse resources, there should be more more collaboration between schools and entrepreneurial programs. With separate communication channels, many divided initiatives and independent audiences, many organizations optimize for their success independently, as opposed to with the larger community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Herein lies the issue. Not one individual piece, but a host of points leads to a constant trial and error development of how to teach entrepreneurship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What can be done? First, the different schools at the University of Michigan must continue to incentivize top entrepreneurs from San Francisco, New York and Chicago to teach entrepreneurship here. This includes providing these entrepreneurs faculty status, and unique incentive structures based on companies they advise and invest in. Additionally, we must lose the stigma that a student studying entrepreneurship is taking the ‘easy path’ or is receiving a ‘second class’ degree. Finally, the future of entrepreneurship will continue to hinge on the success of student organizations. They teach students entrepreneurial skills with a safety net that allows them to fail. Faculty must continue to fuel the creation of new entrepreneurial organizations and assist them in creating successful programs for the long-term success of entrepreneurship on campus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are the number three entrepreneurial school in the country. That is incredible. But in the spirit of the University of Michigan and entrepreneurship, we should continue to strive to be the best in the country at fueling innovation on campus and in our students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ilan Siegel is a junior studying public policy at the Ford School with a focus on religion’s influence on world politics. He is currently President of MPowered and is the founder of IgniteIt and PowerCast—MPowered’s first ever Podcast. His interests include power lifting, cooking and reading.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;innovate-for-the-sake-of-our-species&#34;&gt;Innovate for the sake of our species&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jeff Sorensen&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the sake of our future, I hope Michigan becomes a genuine leader in entrepreneurship. I believe this requires three things: recognizing the urgency of the human situation, illuminating possibilities for a future worth living in and taking collaborative action toward that future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The urgency is clear. For the first time in the modern history, we face extinction level threats to our species. Climate change is wrecking our planet at an accelerating rate. Nuclear weapons could do the job even quicker. Racism will likely outlast capitalism, and artificial superintelligence presents tremendous uncertainty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unsettling questions abound. What will humans do if machines take 80 percent of human jobs? What if our environment is strained to the breaking point, refugees converge on cities, water is scarce and billions suffer from inequality? Can we develop the intellectual and moral capacity to control our worst impulses?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the stakes. Utopia is still possible, but we’re accelerating toward a dystopian cliff. The University of Michigan has the potential to help us change course. Unlike a private corporation, we do not aim to maximize financial profit for a small group of shareholders. Instead, we exist to serve the people of Michigan and the world through preeminence in creating, communicating, preserving and applying knowledge, art and academic values, and in developing leaders and citizens who will challenge the present and enrich the future. Will we live up to our mission?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can begin by illuminating possibilities. Might a utopian future include “urban agrihoods” where everyone eats from the local urban farm? How about educational technologies that empower girls to thrive? Maybe smart resource distribution so excess in one location is transferred to meet a need elsewhere – whether that’s food or medical supplies or even energy?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything I mentioned is already being achieved by optiMize students. They’ve created visions and they’re mobilizing toward them. They’re creating startups, nonprofits and movements, all while learning skills you cannot get in a classroom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These students are outliers – for now. If we want to make innovation the norm, we might ask what optiMizers do differently. They spend less time working passively and more time taking action. Classroom learning is not sufficient for the world we live in, and entrepreneurial endeavors offer an ideal supplement. They are self-directed, action-based and collaborative. They’re ambiguous and open-ended. And they map to the reality of an increasingly complex world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2012, I co-founded optiMize because I believe students can change the world. We can unleash that potential by creating supportive environments for students to take action. So far we’ve incubated 300 student-led projects and about 1200 students in total. Our principles are simple. Students work in teams on self-chosen projects with real-world ramifications. Our learning experiences are flexible and aim to inspire. Students learn by doing, and we cultivate a community for mentorship and mutual support. And we have a lot of fun doing it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Michigan wants to innovate toward a future worth living in, perhaps our students, faculty, and alumni could follow the example of the optiMizers. Instead of competing against each other, we can work together. Instead of hoarding resources, we can share and mobilize. Instead of “professing,” we can engage. Instead of worrying about choosing the right concentration, we can focus on the pressing challenges in the world around us. And instead of merely talking about those challenges, we can work collaboratively and compassionately toward a just and sustainable future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sound interesting? Here’s what you can do. Think of something that frustrates you. Learn about it and create a vision of a better alternative. Take action toward that alternative, adapt and take more action. Find a place to work alongside others who support you. Practice love and compassion. And do everything you can to make our campus more accessible and inclusive – we need every perspective in this collaboration. These types of changes could radically alter the landscape of higher education and unleash an unprecedented torrent of creative action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re a student, join us at optiMize. If you’re an alum, support the students however you can. If you’re on faculty, break out of your traditional circles and collaborate with researchers from other disciplines. Make our research a leading force for change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Choosing to act requires courage, but it’s a lot more fun than the soul-crushing status quo. I’d been teetering on the edge of action for years, and my life changed forever on the day I asked myself one question. Try asking yourself right now:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why not me?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jeff Sorensen founded optiMize as a student and is now Director for Social Innovation at the University of Michigan College of LSA. Follow him on Facebook @jpsorens&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;passion-v-paycheck&#34;&gt;Passion v. Paycheck&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Anushree Vora and Vikram Rajagopalan&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today at Michigan, we follow largely pre-professional paths that take us into well-established careers in finance, business, software engineering, medicine and so on. Many students apply to the Ross School of Business not knowing what they want to do specifically, but hoping that the school will provide job security. Freshmen are seduced by the business school’s promise of a higher average GPA than other colleges (for those looking to go to grad school, this is great news), connections, networking and top-notch recruiting. But when are we asking students what they love? What subject can they rant about for hours because they know it fully and in so much depth?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not just Ross – we push students in Engineering, LSA, the School of Information, etc. down career paths too soon for the sake of securing a safe future. Risk-aversion is embedded into every layer of this University, and in order to be the “leaders and best” in entrepreneurship, we need to unlock students’ true passions. We believe that students should be pushed to consider their individuality when in the classroom. Figuring out what students care about will lead to less food delivery and see-when-your-friends-are-free startups and create more projects that have meaningful impacts on campus and beyond. A campus-wide push for passion over paycheck will yield a culture where students won’t just start companies for the sake of starting companies, which is the current state of the Michigan student startup scene.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first step is to stop idealizing entrepreneurship and glorifying the wealthy tech elites. We count Larry Page, Tony Fadell, Dick Costolo and Dan Gilbert as textbook Michigan entrepreneurs, but in painting these highly successful individuals as ideal entrepreneurs, we risk focusing too much on their success, and not enough on their journey. For example, a recent MPowered Facebook post for Judy Faulkner, founder of Epic Systems, repeatedly mentions her $2.2 billion net worth, and invites students to visit her talk to “learn more about how can [sic] achieve a net worth of 2.2 million” By using such high-profile entrepreneurs and making the objective to make off as a billionaire, entrepreneurship seems out of reach and about the money, and not about the problems founders aim to solve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our programs need to put more of a push on self-discovery and self-awareness. Many students enrolled in the entrepreneurship minor will take five or six classes in the department. These classes will largely be designed around starting a project with a team, working with the Business Model Canvas and pitching the startup to local venture capitalists who are friends with the professor. Then, the department asks itself, why aren’t more of these projects surviving after the class ends? Perhaps it is because students have never gotten a chance to connect with a problem that resonates with them and have been asked to build four distinctly different companies through the minor. There was no early push to help students in the program find ideas that made them want to put their all into their classwork. We need more ideation workshops. More introspection. And much less pitching practice and deck-building.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We direct SHIFT Creator Space, a house on campus that emphasizes the importance of working on projects students care about. Our program is extremely tight-knit and mentorship-driven, and our members tend to go on to build their own startups or work at some of the best tech companies in the world. While SHIFT is small, only taking in about 40-50 students a year, we try to make our largest priority focusing on identifying problems creators can fall in love with. We are not an incubator: you don’t have to start up or get out. We are a house of passionate creators that encourage each other to look around the corner when our projects seem to hit dead ends. These passion projects often turn into companies, but there is incredible humility in focusing on what you’re building and what excites you before focusing on what it could turn into.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, being the “leaders and best” in entrepreneurship is about building products that matter – and the only way to do that is by getting students to focus on what they want to build. If we can build more spaces like SHIFT within the University, it is possible to build a more organic and authentic environment in which entrepreneurs can thrive. The key is to focus less on fortune and fame, and find problems students care deeply about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Anushree Vora and Vikram Rajagopalan are directors at SHIFT Creator Space. Anushree previously directed Startup Weekend Ann Arbor and MTank with MPowered. She has spent the last few summers in the Bay Area working at high-growth tech startups. Vikram is also a two-time director at MHacks, and previously worked at Delta on the Innovation Team and in the Bay Area at OnboardIQ (YC S&amp;rsquo;15).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;clear-eyes-full-hearts-go-blue&#34;&gt;Clear Eyes, Full Hearts, Go Blue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Varsha Tirukonda&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The University of Michigan is home to many natural leaders, but helping them to grow into capable entrepreneurs is no easy task. It doesn’t happen overnight and, in most cases, it doesn’t even happen in four years. Still, the glorified idea of becoming a college dropout-turned-startup founder falsely leads students to believe that taking huge risks and diving into the deep end is the best way to succeed. While many dream of being the next Mark Zuckerberg, it’s important to keep in mind that most successful entrepreneurs see success much more gradually. And that’s completely normal. Building a company will be the hardest and most demanding task that any entrepreneur chooses to face, regardless of age or experience. When that decision is made by a college student, the changes can be overwhelming. Fortunately, Michigan can play a key role in helping students develop the skills that make great entrepreneurs while in school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my experience, these skills are best developed in a controlled and low-risk environment. As a director for MHacks, a 36-hour hackathon organized by Michigan students, my goal is to give students a comfortable and empowering creator space. MHacks brings over one thousand students to campus twice a year to build creative software and hardware projects with the latest technology. Participants (“hackers”) spend 36 hours working in teams of 1-4 people to build or code projects (“hacks”) they’re excited about. There are workshops, mentors, and buckets—yes, buckets—of coffee to guide you along the way. You bring your ideas, and we give you everything you need to make them come to life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At its heart, MHacks is an opportunity to flex your entrepreneurial muscles—to stop just thinking about an idea and actually start building it. Hackers experience all the setbacks, roadblocks, and breakthroughs that come with true innovation. While prizes and the potential for employment certainly don’t drive students away, what really gets 1500 students to give up their weekends is a desire to meet like-minded people and learn new skills. MHacks, and hacking in general, embodies the education-first ethos missing from pop culture entrepreneurship. This philosophy is essential to entrepreneurial success at the collegiate level. The university should encourage students to take advantage of the many resources it has to offer, allowing students to take risks and even fail in a safe environment. Failure is often an inevitable part of entrepreneurship, so it’s important that we teach students to embrace their mistakes and use them as a learning opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Events like MHacks and student orgs like optiMize provide the tools and experiences students need to be successful founders when they—and their ideas—are ready. They also get students more involved in the Ann Arbor/Detroit entrepreneurial ecosystem. This past October, MHacks 8 went back to Detroit for the first time since MHacks III to showcase the renewed entrepreneurial spirit of the city. We hoped that this energy alongside Detroit’s deep-rooted history as the automotive industry capital would inspire students with their hacks. We saw some great results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A record number of teams used this energy to create social good hacks. But more importantly, we saw hackers making connections with our Detroit partners and recognizing the potential of the city itself. These relationships are critical to the continued growth of entrepreneurship on campus. With an impressive alumni base, which includes the likes of Larry Page and Dick Costolo, alongside being ranked third for entrepreneurship, it’s obvious that Michigan is doing something right. But graduates with a vested interest in the local community are the ones that will return to Ann Arbor and choose to start their business here rather than in the Bay Area. They’re the key to creating a strong support system and lasting mentorship network for incoming classes of budding entrepreneurs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If raw talent and great ideas were all it took to be an entrepreneur, Michigan would have the leaders and best in spades. In truth, cultivating the leaders and best in entrepreneurship will takes time, resources and above all, faith. More than money or connections, entrepreneurs need people who believe in them and their ideas. Michigan can create the next generation of great entrepreneurs by being deliberate about investing in their long-term success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Varsha Tirukonda is a senior studying Computer Science Engineering and a former co-director of MHacks and Startup Career Fair.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Relevant Are Safe Spaces?</title>
      <link>http://consideronline.org/issues/2016-11-07-how-relevent-are-safe-spaces/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Nov 2016 19:09:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consideronline.org/issues/2016-11-07-how-relevent-are-safe-spaces/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;November 7, 2016
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-shade-of-grey&#34;&gt;A Shade of Grey&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tina Al-khersan&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout this political election, multiculturalism has been a hot topic. However, the idea of valuing differences has plagued America’s history. Because we as a society, and as a campus, have not yet fully succeeded in creating a method that both respects and bolsters the differences among people on campus, marginalized groups are still being targeted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Typically, marginalized communities have been subject to microaggressions, prejudice and discrimination throughout their lives. When these communities are targeted, it brings up painful memories and intensifies their effect. Furthermore, the University of Michigan is perceived as accepting; the jarring reality that discrimination occurs even in places considered home exacerbates the effects. On top of this, students have to manage academics. This all culminates into a feeling of isolation, anger and sometimes fear. To combat these negative effects, safe spaces are often created in order to provide the community with the means to effectively digest the events, find support and recoup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While these spaces have a positive intention, they are also constantly criticized by the media. Prominent figures continue to argue that safe spaces are not relevant. In fact, they say that they create a destructive environment that represses intellectual freedom by keeping students from hearing opposing viewpoints.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do not disagree with these critics when they say that blocking out opposing beliefs threatens intellectual freedom. In fact, I completely agree. Choosing to selectively listen to people based on their viewpoints prevents education, growth and understanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, these critics and I differ because of how we define safe spaces. I believe that commentators have reduced the varying contexts in which safe spaces can exist by focusing on one setting. Because they deem this one context harmful, they claim that safe spaces in all contexts are harmful. Furthermore, they have assumed that political activists on campus define the term in the same manner, but I do not believe that safe spaces are created in response to one type of event or that all safe spaces have the same intention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before defining types of safe spaces, we must first define what is a marginalized community. These groups have less power when compared to the respective majority group. People initially think of race, but religion, socioeconomic status and survivors of sexual assault are also marginalized groups. Already, it becomes apparent that safe spaces can serve a variety of purposes for each group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, in terms of sexual assault, many critics do not discuss how safe spaces can prevent a survivor from being retraumatized. If the survivor has already been targeted, safe spaces can create an atmosphere where the individual can begin to heal. Rather than being a place that shields an individual from opposing viewpoints, it becomes a necessity that preserves a survivor’s personal well being.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, the safe spaces that I have attended did not consider their primary purpose to be protecting attendees from dissenting viewpoints, like critics claim. Rather, some allowed attendees to brainstorm responses and provide resources, while others encouraged discussion of opposing viewpoints. And even if a safe space is created with the intention of no debate, it is because marginalized groups often live their lives outside of that space debating and fighting for equal treatment, which should be a right. These settings might lessen the opportunities one has to learn about dissenting viewpoints, yes, but marginalized communities are bombarded by opposing beliefs that negatively impact them daily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, these safe spaces often serve as the one place where like-minded individuals can gather. That being said, I do agree with critics when they say that not every uncomfortable event or speech with which we disagree requires a safe space; however, where we draw this line is still unclear because unsafe and uncomfortable are relative terms. Furthermore, because marginalized communities are continuously targeted, a safe space may be crafted in response to multiple events although it appears to be responding to only one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, I think that semantics, a lack of definitions and disacknowledgement of varying contexts has stifled the conversation and reduces the topic to black and white. Activists must be careful when they use the term “safe space” so that the meaning is not delegitimized and critics must acknowledge the variety of settings in which safe spaces occur. All in all, we must continue to expand the conversation by exploring the gray areas. &amp;#9724;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tina Al-khersan is a senior studying International Studies and Arabic/Islamic Studies with a focus on comparative culture and identity. She spends her free time working with refugees through organizations like the Karam Foundation and Michigan Refugee Assistance Program.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;on-safe-spaces&#34;&gt;On Safe Spaces&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dominic A. Stanchina&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thinking in the most charitable way possible, the most idealistic, barebones definition I can construct for a safe space on our campus is this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;A place of refuge and recovery for those who are distressed&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One may ask, “Who would ever be opposed to a place like this?” The answer is no one. No one opposes a place exactly like this. What people like myself do oppose is not within the definition. The arbiter of the safe space is the one who decides what warrants a safe space; at the moment, I oppose them. Who is the arbiter on our campus, and why do they exist? The answer lies in the differences of two universities. One is a university of learning, the other is a university of community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At a university where the focus is learning and academics, safe spaces are not necessary because all of those present would endeavor to be challenged and to learn together, and all understand the primary purpose of what they take part in. At a university of learning, community would naturally spring from the social dynamics within education and academic enrichment, and university administrators would answer to professors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At a university where the focus is community, safe spaces are created because all present do not wish to be challenged or to be changed. There is no primary purpose or common goal among students and professors; rather, they desire wholeheartedly to remain the same and to be accepted in the community in whatever way they see fit. At a university of community, learning and academic enrichment are subject to the preservation of an unnatural, designed and directed community, where professors answer to university administrators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The safe space is part of the modern, bloated university of community, and gives rise to questions relating to the extent to which a university should provide for its students. The answers to those questions lie in what makes a university: its professors. The University of Michigan does not operate as a university or exist as one without the educators and mentors who have come together to form it. The University’s only responsibility is to provide what the professors choose to provide to those people who wish to study with, learn from and provide a salary for said professors. When I interact with my university, I should be interacting with that which sets it apart and defines it: my professors. Instead, whenever I interact with my university, I seem to interact with those who play no pivotal role in the goals of the university of learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The University lavishes food upon its students, but I do not expect a professor to provide me with meals. The University constructs massive housing projects, but I do not expect a professor to provide me with a residence. The University maintains management of colossal athletic capital, but I do not expect a professor to provide me with exercise equipment, let alone a stadium. And among all the other unnamed things that I do not ask of my professors, I do not expect them to make an extra special effort to provide a place of refuge and recovery from ideas that may bother me. All these things seem like a student’s responsibility, and not that of my educator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of letting students handle distressing things themselves, either in solitude or among their peers and trusted mentors, the university administrator has decided that it knows best how to handle such things. Rather than have students decide for themselves what could cause distress or discomfort and how to act after experiencing such things, the university of community arbitrarily decides to issue warnings for whatever events seem most detrimental to its vision of a harmonious community. These come in the form of safe spaces under the guise of the protection of a victim. Thus the discussion of new, bold or controversial ideas is vilified and delegitimized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find the trajectory of our campus to be unacceptable. Students and professors do not need an arbiter of safe spaces when they are perfectly capable of fostering community and understanding amongst themselves. I think that it is time for students and professors to honestly establish why they are here and which type of university “here” should be. &amp;#9724;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dominic A. Stanchina is from the Upper Peninsula of Michigan. His major area of study is Classical Civilizations along with separate minor areas of study in Philosophy and Latin. Dominic is currently Vice-Chairman of Young Americans for Freedom at the University of Michigan, a conservative and constitutionalist education and activism group.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;emotional-safety-in-the-midst-of-oppression&#34;&gt;Emotional Safety in the Midst of Oppression&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ini Ubong&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my opinion, safe spaces are necessary on our campus.  There are two good examples that I know of: TransForm and the Coalition for Queer and Trans People of Color, both of which were created, in part, to be spaces for people with marginalized identities. One reason for Coalition’s existence is to serve as a place for LGBTQ (Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, Transgender, and Queer/Questioning) students of color to have a space to get away from racism, homophobia and transphobia.  LGBTQ spaces are mostly white—and often racist—while organizations surrounding racial ethnic identities often leave out the experiences of LGBTQ individuals. TransForm and Coalition, among other places on campus, create safe spaces for me as well as other students to talk about our experiences without invalidation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, a safe space is a place where I know I’m not going to encounter any hateful speech or identity-based violence, so it&amp;rsquo;s an area where I’m allowed to talk about aspects of myself that might be ridiculed somewhere else. Some of these places on campus are the Spectrum Center, MESA, the M-STEM office and even the offices of some professors. The people in these places understand homophobia, transphobia, racism and other forms of power-based violence; when I talk about my experiences, I go to these people with the assurance that I won’t be invalidated, that I won’t be told that I’m “making things up” or “being too sensitive” or “playing the race card.”  Even if I don’t hold the same experiences as the people I’m talking to, it’s still helpful to be validated, especially in light of recent events on campus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think of safe spaces as places that include content warnings for the discussion of difficult topics, and as places that are guaranteed to be anti-racist as well as affirming of LGBTQ identities. Within the last few weeks, we’ve had white supremacists on campus along with online mockery of transgender identities from the #UMPronounChallenge. It’s been a difficult time for Black and trans students, and doubly so for the people at the intersection of these two identities. Safe spaces have been absolutely necessary for dealing with both of those events. I think it’s important to remember that while these actions were widely publicized, marginalized students deal with microaggressions every day, and safe spaces are a way to talk through it with people who will understand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, designated spaces that are free from oppressive language are good for everyone, and can serve to make this campus safer.  I’ve seen a lot of pushback recently against the idea of safe spaces, trigger warnings and what’s been called “PC culture,” but I find it pretty ridiculous and even selfish. It’s easy to not talk about someone’s trauma in front of them or to not use transphobic slurs. It might take a little extra work, but I think prioritizing the well-being of already oppressed people is worth it. &amp;#9724;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ini Ubong is a senior in LSA studying Biomolecular Science and African Studies.  They are involved with two student organizations: TransForm and the Coalition for Queer and Trans People of Color.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;freedom-of-only-some-speech&#34;&gt;Freedom of (Only Some) Speech&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Talia Katz&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No one would dispute that college should help you discover your passions, sharpen critical-thinking skills and produce exceptional leaders. However, universities absurdly go to extreme lengths to treat students like fragile little flowers. They safeguard students’ idealism by protecting them from having their ideas challenged or feelings hurt. They reinforce students’ complacency with their worldviews and comfort with their ignorance. Universities are increasingly silencing any opinion someone might deem offensive, averse to the core beliefs upon which others were raised, or contrary to someone’s perceptions of truth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brandeis University retracted its plan to award women’s rights activist Ayaan Hirsi Ali with an honorary degree because of her critiques of Islam. The University of Hawaii prohibited students from distributing copies of the Constitution of the United States outside of its designated “free speech zone.” Brown University cut then-NYPD Commissioner Raymond Kelly’s speech short because students were interrupting his lecture by shouting accusations of racial profiling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These incidents are just the tip of the iceberg. According to FIRE, the Foundation for Individual Rights in Education, nearly 62 percent of universities in the United States enforce restrictions on written or verbal expressions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately for those sheltered by trigger warnings and safe spaces, America is a free speech zone, and after you graduate, you cannot whine and you cannot hide to protect yourself. The inauthentic and artificial environment that the university tries to foster for its students could very well produce the most unprepared and ill-equipped generation in American history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the efforts of colleges to shelter students from disillusionment do not stop with ‘uninviting’ lecturers and blatant disregards for our First Amendment. For example, the University of Michigan unveiled its five-year “Diversity, Equity, and Inclusion Strategic Plan” at the beginning of this year – a plan that focuses on supporting students regardless of race, religion, ability or ethnicity. This idealistic goal is noble, but one important component that is missing from this goal is that of opinions and ideas. Only one agenda, one political leaning, one form of opinion can be tolerated both on my campus and campuses around the country. Time and again, if a student or professor expresses a difference in opinion, other students will accuse such contrarians of being “racist,” “fascist,” “homophobic,” “elitist,” and the like. These hyperbolic accusations rationalize safeguarding a student’s right to not be offended at the expense of other students’ individual rights and freedoms to provoke a discussion. Furthermore, this inflammatory rhetoric closes the door to any form of debate or free exchange of ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a student often with the minority opinion, I frequently fear that I would be shunned or silenced for simply expressing my thoughts or offering a counterexample. Some people seek me out to confess to me in private that they are politically right-winged and are afraid to publicly identify as such for fear that both the academic and social portions of their college experience would fall apart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although my thoughts are under attack almost daily, I am not asking anyone for their sympathy; rather, we should sympathize with the liberal student, the social justice warrior and the student who expects society to change for them. These restrictions on free speech hinder these students from criticizing their own ideas or understanding the nuances of complex issues that the next generation must resolve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If intellectual stimulation and the free exchange of viewpoints is the ultimate goal of the collegiate experience, only those who invite debate and unabashedly express their opinions will graduate smarter and more mature than when they stepped onto campus for the first time. &amp;#9724;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Talia Katz is a current sophomore at the University of Michigan in the Honors Program at LSA. She is an indoor cycling instructor, a student ambassador for Prager University and the president of ILEAD, an Israel advocacy group on campus.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>http://consideronline.org/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Nov 2016 21:05:33 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consideronline.org/about/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;We are Consider, a point/counter-point publication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meet some of our team members!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;president-samantha-wintner&#34;&gt;President: Samantha Wintner&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;image00.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Samantha&#34; style=&#34;width: 200px;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sam is the president and editor in chief of Consider! She is a senior in the Ford School concentrating her policy studies in international economics and development, and minoring in political science. She loves to travel and spent the Winter 2016 semester studying abroad in London, United Kingdom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;vice-president-sara-ramaswamy&#34;&gt;Vice President: Sara Ramaswamy&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;image06.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Sara&#34; style=&#34;width: 200px;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hailing from New Jersey, Sara is the vice president of Consider! She is a sophomore interested in pursuing communications and information science. Her motivation is her future corgi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;alyssa-sutanto&#34;&gt;Alyssa Sutanto&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;image04.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Alyssa&#34; style=&#34;width: 200px;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alyssa is a member of the marketing team! She is a freshman in LSA interested in communications and organizational studies. She is an Indonesian international student who is currently over 9,000 miles away from home and is loving life in Ann Arbor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;min-jeong-kim&#34;&gt;Min Jeong Kim&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;image02.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Min&#34; style=&#34;width: 200px;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Min Jeong is a member of the design team! Hailing from Hong Kong, she is pursuing a degree in Stamps, specifically in graphic design. Although she is Korean, Min Jeong was born in Shanghai and attended international school in both Shanghai and Hong Kong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;kirsty-mcinnes&#34;&gt;Kirsty McInnes&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;image01.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Kirsty&#34; style=&#34;width: 200px;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kirsty is a member of the publication team. She is pursuing a degree in communications and hoping to minor in writing. She is a member of Pi Beta Phi and loves hiking in Scotland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;alyson-grigsby&#34;&gt;Alyson Grigsby&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;image10.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Alyson&#34; style=&#34;width: 200px;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alyson is a member of the publication team! She is a first year student interested in pursuing a major in political science and a minor in intergroup relations, and is really passionate about social justice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;katyanna-guthrie&#34;&gt;Katyanna Guthrie&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;image09.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Katyanna&#34; style=&#34;width: 200px;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Katyanna is a member of the publication team. She is pursuing a degree in psychology and English in LSA. She is a cat hoarder and owns three rescued cats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;kelsi-franzino&#34;&gt;Kelsi Franzino&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;image03.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Kelsi&#34; style=&#34;width: 200px;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kelsi is Design Director for Consider. She is an Art &amp;amp; Design Senior from Connecticut, and eats salsa with a spoon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;rinette-korea&#34;&gt;Rinette Korea&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;image07.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Rinette&#34; style=&#34;width: 200px;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rinette is a member of the design team. She is in the School of Art and Design and is currently pursuing a degree in fine arts with an economics minor. Her last name is also the name of a country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;adam-trosin&#34;&gt;Adam Trosin&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;image08.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Adam&#34; style=&#34;width: 200px;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adam is a member of the development team and a junior studying economics in LSA. He is from Jackson, Michigan and is the undisputed tallest member of the Consider team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;farhad-hussain&#34;&gt;Farhad Hussain&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;image11.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Farhad&#34; style=&#34;width: 200px;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Farhad is Consider’s Director of Development and a double-major in business and economics, in both Ross and LSA. He is from Bloomfield Hills, Michigan and has a killer three-point shot (put him on any IM team).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;linda-sun&#34;&gt;Linda Sun&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;image05.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Linda&#34; style=&#34;width: 200px;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Linda is a member of the marketing team! She is a Brooklynite and a sophomore interested in pursuing information science and economics. She is hypermobile and can fake a broken arm.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What is the Future of Media?</title>
      <link>http://consideronline.org/issues/2016-10-20-what-is-the-future-of-media/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Oct 2016 19:09:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consideronline.org/issues/2016-10-20-what-is-the-future-of-media/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;October 20, 2016
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-the-shift-to-online-media-isn-t-the-end-of-the-world&#34;&gt;Why the Shift to Online Media Isn’t the End of the World&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By Madison Dettlinger&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Madison is a senior with a double major in English and political science and is working on her thesis in fiction this year. She is the on-campus editor for The Tab as well as an editor for The Every Three Weekly, and the marketing director for PAWS! She loves to read and her favorite books are the Harry Potter series.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most times, when people tell me I shouldn’t go into journalism because newspapers are becoming obsolete, I give a self-conscious little laugh and shrug my shoulders, hoping to move onto a topic besides my imminent unemployment and the death of the written word. Sometimes, however, I say what I’m thinking, which is that journalism isn’t dying, it’s simply changing. And that’s nothing to be afraid of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past few years, print newspapers have seen a startling decline in value, with papers across the country drastically cutting down on circulation. Our major Detroit papers, the Free Press and the Detroit News, have each reduced their circulation to only three days a week. Things aren’t looking good for newspapers. So why haven’t I hung up my notebook and fled toward a more stable career path like, say, consulting? Because while newspapers are closing their doors, the demand for news is not going down. The need for thought-provoking written work is showing itself in a new medium online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent this past summer in New York working for The Tab, a national publication that started in the UK and has since moved to the US. I’m also the editor for our regional affiliate, The Tab Michigan. The Tab is unique in that it operates exclusively online, and the summer gave me a rare look into what that entails, and into the unique benefits of this type of media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For one thing, online media creates a shift in accessibility on a broad scale. In the past, newspapers have had a history of catering to certain groups. Media conglomerates are largely owned by corporations, which may have questionable motives when it comes to reporting the news. Online media creates a shift in which grassroots journalism is more possible, and people have the means to spread information right from the source. It also means that people who can’t afford to drop any extra cash on, say, a Wall Street Journal, can go to their local library and find the news of the day online. At The Tab, I had the privilege of covering Hillary Clinton’s speech in Brooklyn, where we livestreamed the speech from the press box, helping to create wider access.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, readers no longer have to cut out an article from a paper and mail it just to share their opinion. They can post it on their Facebook walls or send it over text and email and receive an instant response. There has never been a more exciting time for sharing and receiving information, and online media is a major part of that. Another major benefit of online media lies in its lack of temporal restrictions. If something of note occurs on campus or in a national setting, we can keep readers updated in real time, instead of waiting until our next printing day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with every new technology, there are risks to online media, as well. In particular, quality of information can suffer when every site is trying to be the first to report certain information. We’ve seen this time and time again with major news networks such as CNN. Incidental exposure is also majorly decreased when comparing online news and newspapers. When you pick up a newspaper and read, say, a sports news article, your eye is still drawn to the rest of the paper, and you’re exposed to other sections like editorial, news, etc. You also may be exposed to different opinions about an issue. In contrast, someone coming across an article on Facebook may only read that article, or may be directed to a site that’s strongly tailored to a certain issue or set of opinions. There’s also less vetting that needs to happen with the internet’s infinite space, which allows for lower quality pieces to take center stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But sites like The Tab are aware of these risks and working every day to help combat them. Readers respond to good, well-written media—whether it’s online or in print—creating a push for online publications to maintain high standards. We fact-check extensively and attempt to bring a wide range of voices to the sphere. At The Tab Michigan, in particular, I’m working on a goal for this year of having more hard news and in-depth pieces, and less opinion articles, so that we have an efficient balance between the two. Being aware of these issues is the first step in combatting them, and ensuring that the shift from print to online media doesn’t correlate with a lowering of standards. Online media is the future, and that doesn’t have to be a bad thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“The need for thought-provoking written work is showing itself in a new medium online.”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;cut-it-down-media&#34;&gt;Cut It &lt;em&gt;Down,&lt;/em&gt; Media!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By Benjamin Decatur&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Benjamin Decatur is a junior studying political science with a minor in business. He serves as the Assistant Editor-in-Chief of Morning Brew and is an active member of Greek Life, serving as the Treasurer of his fraternity. During his free time, Benjamin loves to golf and go to Michigan hockey games.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps American Marine Ira Hayes said it best: “No one ever complains about a speech being too short!” The same can be said about an article in a newspaper. People are so busy these days that it can be tough for even a news guru to keep in touch with what’s going on in the world. In order to stay informed I find myself having to wake up extra early before class in order to read the Wall Street Journal or my favorite magazine Foreign Policy. Coming from a person who values sleep, this is difficult.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is it so difficult to keep up with the news? I believe the answer is quite simple: newspapers, magazines, and cable news are all too lengthy, cumbersome and boring. People are intimidated and don’t even know where to begin, leading many to shun the news altogether. Online articles pose different problems, but are no more effective. For one, it is difficult for anyone to choose between the thousands of articles that are churned out every minute. Second, the most popular articles are typically not “real” news. And lastly, the articles are still too long.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solution to the problem is quite simple too: the future of media lies in short, condensed articles. Last year I began working for Morning Brew, a daily business and technology e-newsletter, founded by two Michigan business students. CEO and founder Alex Lieberman came up with the idea after realizing that many of his BBA peers were not following business news and found the Wall Street Journal and Financial Times to be too dense and dry. Morning Brew largely solves these problems, as it features top stories from the previous day all in a hundred words or less. The brevity of the Brew and its witty, conversational tone has allowed the e-newsletter to expand rapidly across the country and become a fan favorite among millennials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From working for the Brew I have learned that short articles leave everyone better off. If mainstream media were able to explain top stories of the day in less than a hundred words, think of the vast array of topics the public could explore. Readers would no longer be limited to three or four stories, as there is only so much time in everyone’s hectic day, but instead would be able to dive into the world of politics, technology, business and foreign affairs. Condensed media allow people to efficiently stay informed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It cannot be forgotten that conciseness equals accessibility. The shorter the article, the easier it is to grasp. Less text on the page makes it easier and less daunting to jump into a story. Now at this point, some of you might be thinking that 100-word articles would be great, but would lead readers to miss some aspects of the story. That’s fair. But what do people really remember hours after reading an article? The highlights. No one is going to remember the stats, figures or quotes that contribute to articles being so unnecessarily long. This is why the media should cut out the fluff, summarize the story and include hyperlinks to other sources for those who want more information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Critics might also argue that a 100-word limit on a story stifles all creativity for the writers. This could not be more wrong. One of the main challenges Morning Brew faces is that business news, for the most part, is inherently boring. Earnings reports, jobs data and failed mergers can’t possibly compete with reading about the latest nicknames Trump and Hillary have cooked up for each other. But this is where I am challenged. Not only must I get to the heart of the story in very few words, but these words must also jump off the page. The Brew’s sarcastic tone, wit, references to pop culture and analogies make it fun to write and more importantly, fun to read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So wake up mainstream media! Email newsletters that emphasize brevity like theSkimm, with its over 1.5 million subscribers, the Hustle, Finimize and the Brew are beating you. People are excited to read these sources and are thankful for all of the time it saves them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“Condensed media allow people to efficiently stay informed.”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-digital-future-grounded-in-print-values&#34;&gt;A digital future grounded in print values&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By Michael Sugerman&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Michael is a senior in the Gerald R. Ford School of Public Policy with a concentration in the intersection between journalism and policymaking. He has spent the last four years rotating through a plethora of roles on the Michigan Daily, and likes taking walks through the Arb in his free time.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was prompted to write this column with a question about my belief in the future of print journalism, and the fact of the matter is, it’s complicated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could give you the doomsday spiel. Newspaper &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.journalism.org/2016/06/15/newspapers-fact-sheet/&#34;&gt;circulation is falling&lt;/a&gt;, as are revenues. Newsroom employment has been &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.journalism.org/2016/06/15/newspapers-fact-sheet/&#34;&gt;dropping for years&lt;/a&gt;. There are plenty of high-profile examples of newspaper publishing companies declaring bankruptcy. People in our generation increasingly get their political news &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.journalism.org/2015/07/14/the-evolving-role-of-news-on-twitter-and-facebook/&#34;&gt;from Facebook&lt;/a&gt;. Admittedly, none of it sounds good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are problems I’ve witnessed in numerous arenas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an intern in the Office of the Publisher for the Los Angeles Times two summers ago, I was part of a team that was working to make the Times’ content more digitally marketable by exploring a number of strategies — from launching newsletters and podcasts to just encouraging reporters to be more active on social media sites like Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, my previous experiences on the Michigan Daily have been reflective of the issues facing most newspapers. I’ve served in a few roles on the Daily: a student government beat reporter, a senior news editor advising the administration beat and currently, a columnist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During my time as an editor, I was part of the Daily’s internal body of governance, MDesk. Comprised of the publication’s senior editors across all of its sections, MDesk regularly talks about ways to improve Daily content, reach and revenue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our conversations resembled those of the professionals: we argued about redesigns to our website, pitched new ideas for digital news coverage and debated the merit of implementing features like Google Surveys to pump up digital ad revenue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aforementioned “doomsday spiel” comes from the harsh reality that news consumption is changing, whether you’re a professional or a student journalist. But there is an upside. We &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; print journalism, on local and national levels, because journalists do an invaluable service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Journalism is about going behind the scenes and telling the stories that deserve to be told, whether it’s for the sake of checking those in power, contextualizing current events, or simply giving a voice to the voiceless. It’s about making connections with others and satisfying a thirst for information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our standards for “truth-telling” are high, and it’s a responsibility that few other professions bear. Just about anybody can put information online nowadays, which makes it even more important to have journalists as an objective gauntlet for that information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At a time when I see people repost memes with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.factcheck.org/2015/11/bogus-meme-targets-trump/&#34;&gt;falsified quotes&lt;/a&gt; from presidential candidates and factually incomplete or skewed information from über-partisan groups like “Occupy Democrats” on Facebook more than they do hard news articles, I think journalism is more important than ever, and I don’t think it’s going away anytime soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what does the future look like? I’d say it’s digital-first, but from trusted, previously print sources. Facebook and Twitter news use is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.journalism.org/2015/07/14/the-evolving-role-of-news-on-twitter-and-facebook/&#34;&gt;on the rise&lt;/a&gt;; research shows that the online audience for newspapers &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.journalism.org/2016/06/15/newspapers-fact-sheet/&#34;&gt;is growing&lt;/a&gt; and that longform news consumption &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.journalism.org/2016/05/05/long-form-reading-shows-signs-of-life-in-our-mobile-news-world/&#34;&gt;has a following&lt;/a&gt; in our increasingly mobile-centric world. It’s also no coincidence that big print publications like the New York Times, the Washington Post or the L.A. Times have launched free apps and newsletters with daily news briefings, targeted, without a doubt, at younger consumers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among my friends (a skewed sample because of their political leanings and educational levels), I also see the rising popularity of online-first, analysis-driven publications like Vox, FiveThirtyEight or Politico — all sites that are fueled by original reporting on news events from traditionally print publications, and sites that may have originally paved the way for a market driven by thorough and free email newsletters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The drive toward digital has also led to awesome innovations in news reporting, like the incorporation of virtual reality. My takeaway: times are changing, but the basic need for reporting certainly is not. Subsequently, despite cynicism from within and outside of the news industry, I remain resolute in my commitment to journalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few years ago, Detroit Free Press sportswriter Mitch Albom was speaking to a group of people at my synagogue back home. Because I was thousands of miles away at school, my dad asked a question on my behalf about career prospects for young journalists and recorded the response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite admitting certain pitfalls, Albom concluded that journalism is the path to follow “If the passion is true, and strong, and you want to get into it for the right reasons … and that right reason is that there is a beauty in telling the truth, and a need and necessity to tell the truth, particularly now in a world where all that matters is eyeballs.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He called journalism “the most important job you can do.” I agree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“We &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; print journalism, on local and national levels, because journalists do an invaluable service.”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;swimming-up-a-waterfall&#34;&gt;Swimming Up a Waterfall&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By Alex Rakestraw&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Alex Rakestraw is a junior in the Ross School of Business and the Digital Features Editor of SHEI Magazine. He is also a member of the Every Three Weekly and the Michigan Running Club, in addition to writing his own blog at&lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://asrakestraw.com&#34;&gt; &lt;em&gt;http://asrakestraw.com&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;.  &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A mere three decades after creating the “Information Superhighway,” we’ve come to a fork in the road.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On one side lies the path most traveled: popular media will inevitably become more digital. Forty-five percent of the world now has Internet access, and as that number continues to grow, the same fundamental tendencies that link us all will live online as well. As a species, humans seek novelty, convenience and stimulus, all three of which are breathtakingly more efficient to transmit through fiber-optic cabling than pressed letterhead. As Digital Features Editor of SHEI, it is my job to facilitate that transmission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On any given week, I edit 2-4000 words of text, provide everything from language consultation to art direction and publish original content to SHEI’s many-thousands readership, all from a laptop that cost me less than one month’s rent. What used to take a newsroom and a factory press is now the sole charge of a college junior who needs a Google Calendar alert to remember rent is due.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What a time to be alive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The purpose of the above isn’t to flex SHEI’s production ability – instead, it’s all about efficiency. If one bored kid in a Starbucks (whose only real costs are his laptop and a latte) can do what once took the work of many, there becomes a rational economic argument for change. Add in the information commoditization offered by social media and the advent of free-to-consumer, advertising-driven news sources, and that rational economic argument only grows louder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2016, we are living in the aftermath of that conflict’s opening salvo: “new media publishers” like Buzzfeed and the Daily Beast have eaten traditional publishers’ lunch to the point where the formerly-impenetrable stalwarts (the New York Times; Conde Nast) must either adapt to this digitization (and its accompanying revenue models) or face some rather uncomfortable choices. The Times chose T Brand Studio; Conde chose magazine closures. Both were forced into layoffs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short: the future of media is digital. Denying this fact is like swimming up a waterfall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, while our shimmering digital future appears bright at first, it is naught but gilded: the same economic arguments that dictate the print-to-digital transition have directly sown the seeds of digital media’s worst offenses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the last year alone, we’ve seen a tide of ethical breaches directly linked to our hurried embrace of ad-driven, real-time “free” media: Facebook’s trending topics, emboldened native advertisers and the scourge that is algorithmic news filtering. None of the preceding would exist without the new and unfamiliar goal of media to inform people of events that conform to how their world is shaped, not the events that shape their world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simply put, if you wrap that novelty/convenience/stimulus trifecta in content someone already agrees with, that person is more susceptible to your message – whether that’s “vote Trump” or “buy these shoes.” What they are not is an analytical, informed, individual human being.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solution to this stunting of growth lies squarely on that “other path.” I believe the future of thought remains soundly with the past: safely, securely, in print. While those rational economic arguments from the above may mean it’s no longer possible to make a ruinous fortune in publishing, the printed word – in its traditional human-curated, “pay for access” form - must survive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are humans inherently biased? Yes. But in the age of digital media, that bias is mitigated by the tangible publishing of a static object. Printed newspapers don’t change in real time because you googled “Nike sneakers.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, the selection of worthy articles by a vision-driven professional team will provide the diversity of thought needed to nurture a complex, nuanced view of the world. You and I will learn from the same Wall Street Journal, not from personalized newsfeeds that hand-feed us only what we already want to see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For these reasons, it is my firm opinion that digital media is biased against providing the intellectual discomfort human beings need to develop, leaving print media to nurture thought and stoke positive growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To tie it in a bow: SHEI is fortunate enough to publish both on the web and in a biannual printed magazine. While our website is “viewed” by thousands, when writers look to publish the sort of original editorial content that makes an impact on their world, they ask me first to put it in ink.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m more optimistic than I am offended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“Digital media is biased against providing the intellectual discomfort human beings need to develop…”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Who is Responsible for Political Polarization?</title>
      <link>http://consideronline.org/issues/2016-03-24-who-is-responsible-for-political-polarization/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Mar 2016 19:09:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consideronline.org/issues/2016-03-24-who-is-responsible-for-political-polarization/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;March 24, 2016
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;republicans-are-to-blame-they-refuse-to-compromise&#34;&gt;Republicans are to blame. They refuse to compromise.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Allison Hellman&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a fit of rage at the Republican party, my friend declared “I don’t even understand why they let conservatives into this school.” Her statement was obviously shocking, not only for the simple reason that she thought a high school, albeit a liberal one, should reject all people right of center on the political spectrum, but more importantly because it raised the question of what the Republicans had done to incite such a strong response. However, it is true that members of the public are becoming more partisan in their views and the Republican leadership in Congress, as well as right leaning news outlets, are encouraging them. Their emphasis on rejecting com- promise forces conservative voters to the right and gives liberal voters the impression that conservatives are wrong in their ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the Pew Research Center, both parties have shifted away from the center. In the last twenty years, the percentage of Americans who consistently hold either conservative or liberal views has increased from 10% to 21%. However, this is not the only reason why Americans have become more polarized. In the last twenty years there has been an increase in Americans who view members of the other party as “a threat to the nation”, echoing the sentiment about conservatives my friend had. 36% of Republicans and 27% of Democrats would also agree the above statement applies to the other party. The Pew Research Center goes on to show even more metrics of polarization, showing that strong conservatives and liberals don’t even want to live in the same communities with people who have different views than them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The blame for this divide can be placed squarely at the feet of Republican Congressional attitudes and far-right media such as Fox News. The rhetoric of the Congress Republicans in recent years has been heavily focused on standing on principle and not compromising. It has also been focused on dismantling President Obama’s ideas and attacking his legitimacy. One of the worst examples of this was when Republican senators used a government shutdown as a political tool. In 2013, the government shut down because Republicans would not agree to the provisions in Obamacare and so no financial plan was passed. Senator Ted Cruz, who recently won the 2016 Iowa Caucus, has said that “Republicans need to actu- ally do what we say we’ll do. It was not a mistake for Republicans to stand up and fight Obamacare.” In the same interview, he also supported a plan to force another government shutdown over Obama’s views on immigration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other culprits responsible for increased polarization are the far right media. Their shows and websites have suggested that Obama is not American, but a Muslim and a dictator. The so-called “birther” views persisted throughout Obama’s entire first term as president, coming up as an election issue in 2012. Additionally, 14 Republican congressmen voiced doubt over Obama’s right to be president because of his alleged place of birth. Talk show host Michael Savage proclaimed that Obama was a Muslim, while Insight on the News claimed he secretly studied at a madrassa in Indonesia. Fox News, the most mainstream of these sources, consistently shares quotes claiming Obama is a dictator, such as the statement made by NRA CEO Wayne LaPierre early in 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point of the examples above is to show how Republicans, in the public eye, are creating an extreme view of the party as a whole. This is a large cause of the increased partisanship in America today. Republicans who see these statements and attitudes, especially if it’s their only source of political news, are more likely to shift right to agree with their elected officials and media to fit what they now see as the standard “conservative” mold. Democrats who see a refusal to compromise and distrust of a Democratic president from prominent conservatives are likely to think that all conservatives have views like this. This causes them to believe that the Republicans are both crazy and against Democrats, so they shift as far away from the them as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not to say that the Democrats are blameless, nor that all Republicans share the view of the individuals above. The Democrats in Congress absolutely create deals that Republicans will never sign, forcing them to stand on principle. The difference is that the Democratic establishment does not have a ‘refusal to compromise’ as part of the message it sends to the public. Left-leaning news outlets never circulated a numerous amount of rumors that questioned the legitimacy of say, George W. Bush. Again, it is also true that not all Republicans have extreme views, but a lot of the ones in the spotlight do, while ones with more moderate views, like John Kasich, are cast aside. The vast group of moderate conservatives, who I fully believe exist, is encouraged to mirror their most visible leaders and shift right, causing liberals, like my high school friend, to put all conservatives together into a group they consider so repulsive that they believe they are a threat to our nation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Allison Hellman is a freshman in the LSA Honors Program and the Residential College at the University of Michigan. She is from Woodbridge, Connecticut and plans on majoring in Biology. Allison is the Party Leader of the Left in the Michigan Political Union and an active member of the Michigan Running Club and Michigan Triathlon Club.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;democrats-are-to-blame-they-divide-the-people&#34;&gt;Democrats are to blame. They divide the people.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;William Presley&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s sweeping across college campuses like wildfire, infecting many and causing annoyance and inflammation wherever it’s found. No, I’m not talking about Gonorrhea, but rather political correctness (though for the life of me I can’t tell you which I’d rather deal with). Everywhere, so-called social justice warriors, armed with wagging fingers and stylish fedoras, throw tantrums in the name of language policing. They often find themselves the target of immense anger, which is understandable given that their movement is, on the surface, an attempt to stifle free speech so that big, bad reality can’t hurt the feelings of a few ‘special snowflakes’ among us. However, upon deeper reflection, it becomes clear that they are deserving also of sympathy, as they are merely tools used by the Democratic establishment to quiet those who threaten to expose their true agenda: divide and conquer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, anytime an issue has arisen that threatens to create a barrier between two large groups of the population, the Democrats have taken the opportunity, not to act as a unifying force, but to create a bigger wedge. When Michael Brown was killed during an attempted assault on a police officer, for instance, racially-charged riots ensued. Instead of using his position as a platform to condemn the attack that led to the fatal shot and urge the rioters to behave like members of civilized society, President Obama added fuel to the fire by sending three aids to the Brown funeral to be seen alongside professional race-baiter Al Sharpton.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, such actions are not uncommon from our current president. This is a man known to stand on the graves of dead children to push his gun control agenda and angrily brand those who dissent as ‘bitter clingers’ when he doesn’t get what he wants. But then again, how does that old saying go? If at first you don’t succeed&amp;hellip; try again? No, that’s not it. How about if at first you don’t succeed, play Americans against each other to the point of political chaos? There we go, that sounds about right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, I’m not being entirely fair here. By focusing only on Obama, I don’t give his fellow leading Democrats enough credit for their efforts to divide Americans. Take for example the matter of the ‘gender pay gap.’ The idea itself is a complete fallacy based on a politically charged, scientifically inaccurate study that isn’t recognized by a single credible economist. The only reason that the term hasn’t completely vanished from our vernacular at this point is that it has been seized upon by individuals like Hillary Clinton and Bernie Sanders, one of whom will be the Democratic nominee (or indicted), to perpetuate the existence of the ‘war on women.’ Now, you’re not going to convince me that either of the aforementioned candidates are stupid&amp;hellip; no common idiot could make it as far as they have. That leaves only one plausible explanation as to why they would continue&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;to spout off on a fantasy as ridiculous as their imagined war: they wish to turn women into purple-haired adversaries of the fictitious patriarchy. In other words, their goal is to create contention between women and men.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are just a few cases off of an innumerable list that illustrate the Democrats’ proclivity for division. Whether it be over a necessary solution to an eminent problem or a sound bite taken out of context, the Left seems to possess a special talent for dividing Americans into groups, labeling some, usually their political opponents, as ‘oppressors’ and others, usually minorities and women, as ‘oppressed.’ It is then that they, the white knights, may swoop in and rescue all of society’s ‘victims’ from the clutches of those evil Republicans&amp;hellip; for the price of a vote, that is. And what happens when we Republicans catch on? What happens when one among our ranks stops playing the game and threatens to reveal their tactics? The politically correct drones are deployed to silence them with shouts of “Racism! Sexism!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Albeit funny that the party who gave us Robert “Sheets” Byrd and Bill “Slick Willy” Clinton should suddenly pretend to care about either, this cannot continue. The growing chasms Leftists are creating among Americans are feeding an ideological firestorm that translates into partisan gridlock in Washington. Democrats won’t reach across the aisle, as that would be seen as a betrayal of the ‘victims’ they represent, and Republicans can’t without making those who have been unfairly demonized by Liberals feel like they’ve been left out in the cold. This has been a reality for far too long, and until it’s stopped, we are rendered unable to advance as a country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;William Presley is currently a freshman at the university with plans to continue on a pre-med track, majoring in biomolecular science. To date, he has published two novellas, A Letter from Hell and Blissful Insanity, as well as a short story due to appear in an anthology this coming spring.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dating Apps: Can You Call it Love?</title>
      <link>http://consideronline.org/issues/2016-02-18-dating-apps-can-you-call-it-love/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Feb 2016 19:09:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consideronline.org/issues/2016-02-18-dating-apps-can-you-call-it-love/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;February 18, 2016
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;tinder-is-no-substitute-for-time&#34;&gt;Tinder is no substitute for time&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Denis McGrath&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an 18-year-old male who is decidedly single and unmarried, the question of whether dating apps such as Tinder are changing the ways people meet people is a challenging question to answer. I haven’t yet gone through the experience of trying to find my future wife in settings other than high school or my freshman year of college, so I can’t claim to know the objective truth on this matter. That being said, my experiences thus far with dating apps have convinced me that dating apps are definitely changing the way that people are meeting nowadays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our society, time is at a premium. In every aspect of life&amp;ndash; from school to work to social life&amp;ndash; being incredibly productive and successful has become a requirement. As a result, being successful in any field requires more and more effort, which takes away from time in other areas. This emphasis on the value of time can be seen in situations such as the emphasis on joining “select” sports teams and focusing on one sport as opposed to becoming pretty good at multiple different sports or with the incredible workloads being placed on high school students so that they can be competitive to get into prestigious universities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think that the increased value of time has led to the proliferation of social media. People attempt to box their lives into 140 characters or a brief profile picture and caption, and based off of this streamlined version of themselves, they try to find people with similar interests to be their “friends”. It’s only natural that in a social media society, social media dating apps such as Tinder have followed closely behind, with people attempting to find their next significant other or next one-night stand based off a couple pictures and a brief profile.  Quite frankly, people don’t have the time to follow in the footsteps of older generations and spend hours upon hours at bars getting to know the perfect person, so they turn to social media and social media dating apps in the interest of time. However, while social media and social media dating sites have helped our generation adapt to its increasing workload, while still maintaining a social life and continuing to search for the perfect significant other, these sites and apps have increasingly forced today’s generation to compact itself to fit into the brief period of time where someone determines whether to “swipe right” or “swipe left”. People have become their best six pictures and their clever bio, and these social media profiles have replaced the time that people used to spend going on dates to get to know each other. While casual sex and hookup culture is nothing new, the popularity of Tinder and other quick dating apps shows that this casual hookup culture is actually starting to replace dating culture permanently. However, in skipping the vital step of dating to get to know someone well, people are starting to be ground down into purely their looks and the text they can fit into messages and profiles, which is essential to forming a relationship with another person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, while most people don’t necessarily go to Tinder or other “fast hookup” apps in order to find the person they want to spend the rest of their life with, using Tinder and other social media sites is teaching people to compact their entire personality and life into a few quick pictures and sentences. The danger with “easy-hookup” or “social media dating” apps is that experiencing those apps will teach people to condense their personalities and thus when they go out and attempt to form a solid relationship, they are unable to, because they never learned how to express themselves in greater length than the word count allowed by an app. To put things simply, I understand why these apps have become so popular, and I don’t necessarily have anything against them—I mean, what’s the difference between getting drunk at a bar or party and having a one-night stand or messaging someone you “matched” with to have one? —but if people begin to mold their dating approaches around these hookup apps, they will form relationships based on purely superficial and shallow reasons. While I don’t see anything wrong with Tinder or other hookup apps, I strongly believe that there is nothing that can replace the time, effort, and hard work necessary for the formation of a substantial relationship, and I believe that these apps are conditioning our generation to believe that they can skip that critical step of truly getting to know someone, which will inevitably lead to relationship failure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Denis is a freshman in the LSA Honors Program at the University of Michigan. He is from Cincinnati, Ohio and plans on applying to the Ford School. Denis is a training developer for UM&amp;rsquo;s Club Swim Team, competes nationally for Paralympic swimming, and is an active member of UM&amp;rsquo;s Blue Model United Nations Club.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;it-s-still-dating&#34;&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s still dating&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anonymous&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the more controversial subjects these days is the emergence of dating apps, such as Tinder, Bumble, Hinge, and many more. These dating apps have gotten a bad reputation by some who believe that they make casual sex and hookups more prominent, thereby making them more of a “hookup app” than a dating app. There are articles warning parents about such dating apps and there is a stigma in society against those who use them. However, I don’t believe these dating apps have changed dating or how we approach our relationships in today’s world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;     Hooking up, casual sex, and the “one night stand” are not new phenomena. They have been around long before dating apps. For people that want to approach relationships in this way, Tinder is just another way that they can do so. If they wanted to go to a bar and pick someone up instead, that works just as well. In that sense, Tinder is not any different than dating without the use of dating apps. There is still opportunity for people to have casual relationships in the world outside of their iPhone applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;     Technology, on the other hand, is what has really changed our lives. Combining technology and dating doesn’t change our approach to relationships in any way. It is just a more convenient way of meeting other people. In the past, you could meet others by going outside to a coffee shop, fitness class, or anywhere else. Nowadays, people spend much more time on their phones and less time socializing. Therefore, dating apps allow people to still meet others in a world that is becoming more technologically based. Instead of changing relationships, they are changing the way we meet others since original methods have become more obsolete.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;     Not only do dating apps allow you to meet people in a time when that has become harder to do, but also they allow you to meet people that you never would have encountered before. Now you can meet people who have similar interests as you but aren’t in your social circle. Essentially, Tinder and the like are broadening the pool of people to date. This does not change dating; it makes dating more accessible and likely as you have more potential partners to choose between.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;     In the world outside of dating apps, people have many failed relationships and awkward first dates before they find someone right for them. With dating applications, this is exactly the same. In order to find the right person, you may have to face a few losers right off the bat, but eventually you may find the person who is right for you. Whether it is through a dating application, blind dates, or picking up someone at a bar, this is a similar scenario. As you can see from the many Tinder success stories, it is possible to find love through dating apps, just as it is possible to find love without them. Patience and perseverance are always an integral part of dating; this does not change with the use of a dating application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;     In a world obsessed with technology, with people constantly on their cell phones, scrolling through different social media sites, it is no wonder that relationships have been brought to the online world. Dating apps have not changed the way we view or approach relationships. The world is evolving with the growth of technology and dating apps are matching those changes. It is inevitable that as we become more reliant on technology, old forms of meeting people, such as speed dating or blind dating or even matchmakers, are no longer enough. Dating apps use our reliance on technology to allow us to meet more people and expand our circle of possible partners. Dating itself is still the same; there is just a new platform where we can meet partners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;     Our approach to dating has not changed either. If people are looking for something more casual, they can easily find that. If they are looking for something more serious, they can find that as well. We still meet others, now through a larger circle of people, and decide if we get along. In this respect, dating has not changed through the emergence of dating apps. Dating apps allow the millennial generation to meet other people and date, successfully or not, in a world where everyone is staring at their phone.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Should U of M Prioritize In-State Students?</title>
      <link>http://consideronline.org/issues/2016-02-10-should-u-of-m-prioritize-in-state-students/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Dec 2015 19:09:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consideronline.org/issues/2016-02-10-should-u-of-m-prioritize-in-state-students/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;December 5, 2015
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;yes-in-staters-should-be-a-priority&#34;&gt;Yes. In-staters should be a priority.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;by Katherine Smith&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;State universities exist to give students an affordable way to continue their education (though ‘affordable’ may be a generous term for how much it costs to be even an in-state student at the University of Michigan). In exchange for taxpayer support, in-state students get a better rate. These state funds are the vital difference between public and private universities. This support has been steadily declining (and tuition rising as a result) but it is still a substantial amount. State funding amounts to about 16% of the University of Michigan’s general fund, which pays for things like teaching, services, and administrative support. As of last year more than half of all incoming freshmen were enrolling as non-residents. With residents of Michigan paying into the University, it can feel like a betrayal when their students are deferred in preference for out-of-state ones. I experienced this sentiment firsthand. In my senior year of high school, I told a neighbor that I had gotten admitted to the University of Michigan and he replied, “How? You live here.” For him, the growing number of non-residents meant that UM had turned its back on the people in its own backyard. It meant that the University had shirked its responsibilities as a public institution, that the administration was not fulfilling its side of the bargain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;        I understand that there are other sides to this that we, as students, are often unaware of. A freshman enrolling as an out-of-state student will pay nearly $30,000 more than an in-state freshman this year. This difference is extreme and that money can make up gaps in the budget that are left by continually shrinking public support. This solves one problem but introduces another. Filling budget gaps by admitting more out-of-state students with higher tuition costs is contrary to the University’s purpose. If most students are paying private school rates, why be a public school at all? I think the better solution might be to increase support for public universities in Michigan. This facet of the issue is something that the University cannot control. The administration cannot dictate that the state must prioritize public education. Perhaps shrinking public support means that the University has a shrinking responsibility to the state and its students. However, simply changing the student composition to fit the budget seems like a betrayal of the institution’s entire purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from the University’s responsibility to the state, this shift in student composition has a real effect on the campus climate. Students paying the higher rate tend to come from families more equipped to pay it. Because of this, our campus has become home to students from a very diverse geographical range but from a fairly limited socioeconomic one. This colors the campus discourse, from the classroom to casual conversation, to the campus publications. It is not a bad thing to be economically advantaged, and it is actually a very good thing that so many people are willing to pay the exorbitant tuition to come here. It means that our school is desirable and that our degrees will be worth something. However, it also means that we all miss out on a lot of perspectives we could really benefit from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Education is increasingly important and unattainable. Providing an affordable education for young people does a world of good. Aside from the innumerable benefits of the college experience that are more difficult to quantify, a college graduate makes one million dollars more in their lifetime, on average, than someone who did not attend college. None of that matters, however, if a college degree is made impossible by high tuition costs or by a student’s inability to get into a more affordable state school. A high school student that is unable to get into the University of Michigan is likely to gain admittance to another state school, but there simply is no better education in the state than U of M, and admitting more and more non-residents does edge out Michiganders who may be on the brink of admittance. Again, it comes down to whether or not the University has a responsibility to the state of Michigan, and whether or not that responsibility is fulfilled at a 49 percent in-state student composition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The University of Michigan is one of the best public universities in the United States, but in recent years there has been a growing concern about the increase in the number of out-of-state students being admitted. Many worry that in-state students are not being prioritized. In my opinion, in-state students are not only being prioritized but are also receiving more benefits than out-of-state students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;        Not only do in-state students pay less tuition, but they also receive more financial aid. As an out-of-state student, the biggest concern I had when I was accepted to U-M was the tuition and costs, which for fall of 2015 is $57,432 for out-of-state students in their freshman and sophomore year. Tuition is $27,812 for in-state students. Out-of-state students pay a little more than double what Michigan residents do. 70 percent of in-state students receive financial aid versus the 50 percent of out-of-state students that do. From a financial perspective, it appears that U-M is prioritizing Michigan residents over out-of-state students. For the 2016 year, a $1.83 billion budget was approved, which will increase undergraduate financial aid by 8 percent. However, to do this, tuition for undergraduate in-state students will increase by 2.7 percent and out-of-state undergraduate tuition will increase by 3.7 percent. The Michigan Legislature established a 3.2 percent cap to protect in-state students from having a large increase in tuition, but there is no cap for out-of-state students whose tuition has continued to rise over the years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;        In 2014, 49.3 percent of students were from Michigan and 36.9 percent were from out-of-state, which shows a stark decrease in the gap between in-state and out-of-state students. In 2005, 56.5 percent of students were Michigan residents and only 33 percent of students were from out-of-state. However, there is a reason for this. State support this year for U-M is $26 million less than it was 10 years ago. To make up for this gap in funding, it makes sense that the university would look to out-of-state students’ tuition, which would factor into why there has been an increase in admittance for non-Michigan residents. However, this is not prioritizing out-of-state students as U-M is actually receiving more out-of-state applicants than in-state ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;        From the freshman class of 2015, U-M received more than 50,000 applications and accepted a little less than one-third of them. The number of students that have been applying to U-M has been increasing, and more of these applications are coming from out-of-state students. In 2014, out of the 49,731 applications that were received for the freshman class, only 10,000 were from Michigan residents with the rest being from other states and countries. Proportionally, the increase in out-of-state students makes sense, especially combined with U-M’s financial incentives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;        Some concerns have risen suggesting that allowing more out-of-state students would decrease the diversity of the school; in particular, a majority of students with high levels of income that can afford to pay the full tuition would be accepted. I have out-of-state friends who receive financial aid and work-study and friends from Michigan who don’t receive any financial aid. The opposite is also true. I personally have not noticed an income gap between non-Michigan residents and Michigan residents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;        However, it is important to emphasize to those who would argue that a gap does exist, that 50 percent of out-of-state students still receive financial aid. Part of what makes U-M such a diverse and amazing school is that we have students from all 50 states and 114 countries. By increasing the number of students from out of state, U-M is also diversifying the student body with students from all types of backgrounds and experiences.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;        Although in-state students no longer make up half of the student body, they still receive benefits such as paying less tuition and receiving more financial aid. The state government protects in-state students by limiting how much U-M can increase their tuition, a safety net that non-Michigan residents lack. As U-M receives more applicants from other states and receives less funding from the state of Michigan, it can be expected that out-of-state tuition will continue to rise, and more non-Michigan residents will be admitted. This is not, however, prioritizing out-of-state students, but instead prioritizing the diversity and quality of education at U-M.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Are Cultural Halloween Costumes Problematic?</title>
      <link>http://consideronline.org/issues/2016-02-10-are-cultural-halloween-costumes-problematic/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Nov 2015 19:09:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consideronline.org/issues/2016-02-10-are-cultural-halloween-costumes-problematic/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;November 1, 2015
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;because-it-s-pretty-damn-easy-not-to&#34;&gt;Because it’s pretty damn easy not to&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alexandra “the womyn” Friedman&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I begin this argument, I would like to clarify that I don’t have particularly vehement feelings about cultural appropriation in general. I, as a white female, don’t quite know what it’s like to experience appropriation  - which may contribute to my relative indifference to the subject. But what I do know is that there are a lot of Halloween costumes we can choose from (and let’s be real here - 90% of us girls are going to end up as cats anyway).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s relatively intuitive to know what might be offensive to wear as a Halloween costume, which is proof alone that we have some idea that there are costumes we should and should not wear. We don’t dress in blackface anymore because it is trivializing years of historical oppression and making a joke out of being black, which is offensive. We don’t dress up as Nazis for a similar reason - it makes a joke out of oppression. Why would wearing a Native American headdress be any different? Throwing blankets covered in biological warfare to systematically kill Native Americans would _probably _be considered oppressive by today’s standards (considering telling a girl she looks pretty is oppressive according to some people’s criteria). Why must we specifically decide to wear outfits crudely resembling those we have stepped on in our recent history?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most people would not find anything offensive about wearing a taco, a samosa, or a bowl of white rice to Halloween, although these are also symbols of culture. However, when I mention wearing a Mexican mustache, a turban, or a straw conical hat, most people’s intuitions feel a little bit uncomfortable with these images included in a costume. Why do we internally “cringe?” These objects have been included in derogatory slurs, images, or caricatures of immigrants. I’ve never heard anyone call someone else a “f**ing taco”. We like tacos. It’s not _just _the images of foreign cultures that are automatically offensive; it’s the &lt;em&gt;combination&lt;/em&gt; of characteristic images being used to elicit prejudice that makes us feel a little squirmy. You know what you probably shouldn’t wear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But even if you don’t believe that wearing a Halloween costume isn’t important enough to really offend someone, the bottom line is that it’s honestly not that hard. There are a million Halloween outfits someone could wear. Are you really that lazy that you have to dress up like a standing Mariachi toy? Are you really that bothered that despite the fact that I could find you twenty different “sexy police” costumes themselves, we’re asking you to avoid maybe a total of five costumes that misrepresent years of culture being destroyed by our ancestors? For one night? Even if you think you are glorifying or admiring this person’s culture by wearing their clothing, you are probably wearing it wrong. And even if you wear it right - consider the fact that you, as someone who doesn’t face discrimination for wearing this costume, get to wear these outfits to the much glee and approval of others, while those who the culture belongs to face prejudice and marginalization for being “ethnic”. Being exotic isn’t cool when you have to do it every day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The amount of inconvenience changing your costume causes you compared with the obvious amount of distress, annoyance, and outcry it is causing those being marginalized (even when some of those people are clearly overzealous) is minimal. Who cares if some people take it too far? Are you that prideful that you have to defend yourself by wearing a sombrero?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a feminist, there are plenty of women who I consider to be far too radical for my liking. They advertise that all men should die, all sex is rape, and all pornography is vile. Does that mean I should dismiss feminism because there are people who are insulting activities that I enjoy? I choose to retain the beliefs I both believe to be reasonable and do not denigrate others. But if an extremely opinionated feminist approached me and asked her only to address her as a “womyn” or else she would have a panic attack due to being classified as an oppressive gender, I would. Because I wouldn’t feel like dealing with the consequences, and it’s pretty easy to fit this need. If she told me that I would have to do 20 pushups, I wouldn’t - because that is highly inconvenient for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact that I am even being asked to write an article about this topic is evidence enough that this is important enough to be discussed. So who really cares if you believe you are wronging those who are marginalized? It’s not that hard. Pick a different costume. I’ll find you one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Alexandra is an Ecology Major during the day and Social Justice Wario during the night. (Yes, she dons a Wario outfit and slices the throat of chauvinist men.) You will probably find her ranting about the drug war during non-class hours or hula hooping in overly conspicuous places.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;not-offensive-just-for-fun&#34;&gt;Not Offensive, Just for Fun&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Salvatore DiGioia&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s Halloween season and therefore fair to assume that Americans nationwide are stocked up or munching on on Hershey’s snack-sized variety packs as we speak. We also could assume that the more creative consumers are somewhere standing over a sewing machine, carefully crafting their combinations of rubber masks and cheap linen. According to Google Trends, the most popular costume choices this year are superheroes and Star Wars characters, but it’s an age-old tradition that the most bold personalities prove themselves on October 31st. A new tradition is that costume-boldness seemingly going too far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;        We are living in the age of sensitivity, a time when tolerance is considered among the most sacred of personality traits. Highly-esteemed institutions such as the University of Michigan spend thousands of dollars to campaign against the casual use of words like “gay” and “crazy.” We are, at the given moment, hyper-conscious of our political correctness. For the younger generations, those of us bound to college campuses and an inevitable eternity of yuppie coworkers, this is only the beginning. But for Halloween, especially its more risqué embracers, this could be the end. Long gone are the days when snot-nosed teenagers proudly laughed at insensitive costumes. Instead, welcome to a time when a poorly thought-out depiction can easily be caught on camera and earn its designer immediate viral humiliation. Things have changed indeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;        Most cases of offensive attire revolve around racial and ethnic stereotyping. Earlier this year, Walmart faced a public relations disaster for selling a “Little Amigo” costume that imitates Mexican culture with a striped serape shirt, straw hat, and mustache. Then just last week, MTV used an online video to draw attention to similarly tasted get-ups, namely “China Boy” and “Indian Brave.” People aren’t laughing anymore. But why is Halloween being made into the battle ground? Is there something about the quest for free candy that excites people’s innermost vulgarity? To answer this, we must first ask ourselves what motivates a person to slip into one of these outfits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;       Even in the most disrespectful scenarios, I imagine that there’s seldom a sincere desire to offend. Most people choose to cloak themselves in corny latex liner because, since they were old enough to know that ghosts are scary, it’s been drilled into their subconscious that on Halloween people pretend to be something that they’re not. Whatever it is they choose to disguise themselves as, they’re wholly recognizing that their representation of it is in fact fictional. How do you succeed in selling inauthenticity? You build on the preconceived notions of your onlookers, trying to convince them what you “are” without ever speaking a word. That is, by definition, the point of a costume.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;        So when an individual decides to spend the night dressed as a person of Mexican descent, or a Native American, or an Italian, he’s forced to build on his peers internalized understandings. If he wears a sombrero, or a feathered headdress, or an apron with a pizza chef’s hat, he is doing so because it’s how, on a societal level, Americans perceive those cultures. Costumes are meant to convince. If any of these do so successfully, by simplifying remarkably thorough cultures into a single outfit choice, than there’s more than one culprit involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;        Controversial costumes are just an annual excuse to draw attention to a larger, constant issue. Outfits that cross the line only do so by building on images that have been consistently set forth by mainstream media and upheld by real-world experiences. Why might a person think embroidering a dragon onto a robe makes for a Chinese costume? Perhaps it’s because of the identically simplified marketing techniques applied by Chinese restaurants everywhere. If calling a costume that mimics Mexican culture “Little Amigo” is racist, then maybe Mexican restaurants should stop employing similar titles. Maybe, just maybe, if feathers and body paint are a poor portrayal of Native Americans, then we should talk about films like _Dances With Wolves _more often than less-accurate, highly-glorified Disney depictions. The costume wearer isn’t single-handedly sustaining the stereotypes; there’s an institutional problem that transcends the month of October.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;        Halloween costumes merely point out a problem with the entire nation’s understanding of other ethnicities. As far as the costume wearers, they are only lightheartedly pretending to be something other than themselves. They’re dressing up for one night. Are they really the root of concern? It’s not their fault that the world around them has no idea what is authentic. Instead of attacking the festive spirit of Halloween, we should take a step back and think about the fact that people immediately recognize what these costumes are supposed to be. &lt;em&gt;That&lt;/em&gt; might be something worth discussing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Salvatore is a nineteen year old caffeine-addict whose desire to be a writer is equally rooted in Jack Kerouac’s romanticized mishaps and Kanye West’s digital culture. To truly understand him is to know that New York will forever be home and marinara sauce is indigestible unless it was cooked by his mother.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Zombies vs. Aliens</title>
      <link>http://consideronline.org/issues/2015-04-01-zombies-v-aliens/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2015 19:09:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consideronline.org/issues/2015-04-01-zombies-v-aliens/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;April 1, 2015
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;alien-invasion-a-crisis-you-can-survive&#34;&gt;Alien Invasion, A Crisis You Can Survive&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brian Fulper&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;       Not everyone is a hero, and in most zombie apocalypse scenarios you’re almost certainly a casualty, not a survivor. The only way society is threatened by a zombie outbreak is if a majority of the population is infected and knocking on your door for brains. And let&amp;rsquo;s face it, more likely than not, you would be one of the infected. If you’re reading this you’re most likely a student in a housing complex, leaving you at a high risk of being trapped in a corridor with few exits and many zombies surrounding you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;        Even if you&amp;rsquo;re not part of the first wave of infected, most people don&amp;rsquo;t have the survival skills to last without the creature comforts of society. Unless you’re proficient in combat, have survival skills, or are valuable enough that other people would risk their ass for you, you’re a deadman. Even all of these qualities don&amp;rsquo;t protect you if you forget to wash your hands (or fall victim to whatever vector of infection it ends up being) early on in the apocalypse. If you can sleep through the sound of people moaning and banging on your door (normally a very valuable attribute in a dorm) you’re probably already a goner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;        Everyone talks how they have a shotgun, chainsaw, katana, etc. with a some energy bars and a first aid kit in their closet, but the reality is that all this will most likely be looted by a hero/heroine who knows how to do parkour, shoots like an American sniper, and can start a fire by rubbing sticks together. Unless you fall in this distressingly small category (thank the education system for that), your feeble attempt at survival are only good for helping you sleep at night until you inevitably develop a taste for sweet fatty brains in your un-death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;       If you truly want to plan for survival, plan for what you have a chance of surviving, and as far as your chances go, you are more likely to survive an alien invasion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;        Let talk numbers. The Drake equation provides an estimate for the number of alien civilizations capable of emitting detectable signals into space, and while its exact value varies depending on whom you talk to, it’s easy to argue that it’s non-zero (we have ourselves, after all, to prove that life is possible in the universe).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To date, 1,821 exo-planets have been discovered. Data from the Kepler space telescope has dramatically increased the number of observed planets, and allowed us to confirm that some of them may even be habitable. Astronomers are still analyzing the data it sends back, but suffice it to say that every single one they find increases the probability that we are not alone in the universe. Categorizing exo-planets as habitable also presumes that aliens share a similar biology to us, and require the same things we do (air, water, moderate temperatures). This is not necessarily true, and thus creates a potentially lower estimate of the amount of life in our universe than if we were to consider what other types of alien life might exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stephen Hawking, the leading astrophysicist of our time, has even speculated that given our own destructive behavior toward our planet, hostile alien life would want to strip our planet of resources. Therefore, if aliens are invading, we can deduce that they are not friendly, and are threatening our existence (or at the very least after one of the many shiny, glowy, or flammable things we dig out of the dirt).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;        Your best course of action to defend yourself (and your planet) from invasion is to be prepared to fight off the aliens by tooth and nail. It is my opinion that the best teeth and nails often take the form of high explosives. The rocket launcher (also known as the “noob tube” for its ease of use) represents an excellent balance of high explosives and compactness. Therefore I propose that your survival-bag should not be energy bars and whatever weapons you can obtain a license for, but simply a rocket launcher and some courage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the exponentially spreading horror of a zombie infection being out of the picture, the collapse of society will be more controlled, and your ability to survive is proportional to your ability to flee whatever major urban center is being attacked. As long as there is an organized force fighting off the aliens, you can still expect to have the benefits of a semi-functioning society. Not only that, but most of your college degree skills are still useful, you still need engineers, biologists, and physicists to develop technology to defend against the alien invasion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not everyone is a hero, but some courage and a rocket launcher at least make you useful in defending your planet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brian started his career in computer magic at a young age by reading ancient tomes of ‘C’ found in his basement. He currently spends most of his time pressing mechanical switches to make the dots on the box he looks at all day change color in the right order. He impatiently awaits the singularity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;destroying-the-brain&#34;&gt;Destroying the Brain&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joel Reynolds&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think we’ve all shouted at our TV during a good horror movie. There’s always that one character who is just too stupid to live. The person that’s happy to walk right up to the dark and creepy house, content to assume that the last zombie is &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; dead this time. As the dark figures begin to shuffle up behind them, we shout and groan for them to just turn around. “The exit is &lt;em&gt;right&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;there!&lt;/em&gt; Don’t stop now to examine that dusty old photo! You’re gonna die!” Then the camera pans away and a splash of blood hits the wall, accompanied by a blast of scary stinger music as the audience squeals and boos at their stupidity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s at that point that we all lean over to that one friend in particular and say, “If _I _was in that situation you know I would get out of there. Or at the very least fight my way out, not do something &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; stupid.”  And why wouldn’t we? Zombies have become so popular that it’s hard to find anyone who wouldn’t know how to kill one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today it seems a zombie apocalypse wouldn’t get very far. I believe that humans could win in a matter of weeks. When considering slow-moving corpses versus the dominant species on planet, it’s a wonder how zombies are even considered a threat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the land of fiction, zombies wipe out 95% of the world within a few months and only the toughest, most bearded bad-asses survive and slowly rebuild mankind. But have you ever noticed that in those stories zombies are practically unheard of? These shows and movies seem to take place in a magical realm where no has ever even seen a zombie movie. The human characters always have to figure out on their own how zombies work. Someone always has to get bitten so we can see the gruesome transformation in every stage, and someone always needs to get that one lucky headshot so we all know how to kill the walking dead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back over in reality, zombies and zombie-related media saturate the market. They are on T-shirts, are the enemies in our video games and the subject of countless comic books. You would be hard pressed to find anyone unfamiliar with how zombies work. And that is exactly why the zombie hordes will never get far when they inevitably rise from their graves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every nerd and his mother have a plan for the zombie uprising, from a simple crowbar in the garage to an actual apocalypse bunker in the basement. When the zombies come, a civilian militia is literally seconds away from mobilization. The hordes of zombie fan-boys who dream of thrilling adventures and heroics in post-apocalyptic America, will probably be at the front lines, going to town with their chainsaws.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyone bitten would know their fate is sealed and would act accordingly, asking their friends to “make-it-quick”, or go out in a blaze of glory. No one in today’s zombie crazed society would look at their infected bite and say, “Yeah… let’s just hide this and I’m sure I’ll be fine.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Humans are a bit smarter than the writers of horror movies give us credit for. We know not to put ourselves in danger. We know how to defend ourselves. As selfish as we can be, no one would endanger the people they care about. These human qualities are the exact opposite of what you need for to write a good zombie centered narrative. The romanticized vision of sexy, grizzled survivors, arguing and bickering while running from hordes of the undead is much more marketable than a few determined nerds with common sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the dead rise and roam the streets, it’s a safe bet to say it won’t last long enough to even classify it as an apocalypse. A really bad weekend maybe, but never an apocalypse. The brains will be destroyed and the few that get bitten will be handled on their own terms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite all the rations, radiation suits, shotguns and fire axes we gather, the best defense the human race has is the fact that we aren&amp;rsquo;t fictional characters. So while the over-saturated market of zombie love may seem like a fad, it shows that we aren&amp;rsquo;t actually stupid enough to take that ill-fated shortcut through the graveyard after all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joel Reynolds is a student at the University of Michigan. An aficionado of everything geeky, his pastimes usually revolve around graphic novels, video games, animation and art.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sex Education</title>
      <link>http://consideronline.org/issues/2015-03-18-sex-education/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Mar 2015 19:09:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consideronline.org/issues/2015-03-18-sex-education/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;March 18, 2015
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;birds-bees-and-bias-the-real-facts-on-sex-ed&#34;&gt;Birds, Bees and Bias&amp;hellip;The Real Facts on Sex Ed&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Valerie Huber&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past 20 years, you might be surprised to learn that teen sex among high-schoolers has decreased by more than 15% - even in the midst of an increasingly sexualized culture. In fact, nearly 75% of the students most often targeted for sex education (15-17 year olds) have never had sex. Most of these teens, in fact, have had no sexual contact at all. Wouldn’t it make sense, then, for our sex education programs to reinforce these behaviors and even increase healthy decision-making by providing the encouragement and skills for teen sexual delay?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is exactly what Sexual Risk Avoidance (SRA) abstinence programs do!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SRA message resonates with teens because it is holistic and is consistent with the public health message that recognizes that every teen deserves the information and skills to avoid all the negative consequences of sex, so they have the best chance to thrive and achieve optimal sexual health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By contrast, Sexual Risk Reduction (SRR) programs normalize teen sexual experimentation and focus almost exclusively on teen pregnancy prevention through the discussion of consent and effective contraceptive negotiation, but they fail to recognize that sex often affects a person beyond genitalia – and that while risk is reduced – risk still remains.  This approach is often called “comprehensive” sex education but it is anything but, yet 96% of all federal sex education dollars are devoted to such programs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Youth deserve realistic and accurate information so they can successfully transition to adulthood without engaging in activities that have the potential of putting their future goals and dreams out of reach. That’s why SRA programs empower youth with the skills they need to become productive and successful members of society, to form healthy interpersonal relationships, and to delay sex until the children they eventually bear have the best chance for personal and economic success Conservatives and liberals alike have come to recognize the best formula for success involves following a sequence of behaviors that constitute the core for many SRA programs.  Called the “success sequence,” the Brookings Institute revealed that youth have only a 2% chance of living their adult lives in poverty if they graduate from at least high school, then get a job, then get married, and have children after marriage. So SRA programs contextualize the conversation about teen sex around the fact that the teens years are better focused on education and future goal-setting rather than sex, that avoiding all negative risk behaviors increase their chances for success, and that learning how to identify and build healthy relationships and avoid or escape unhealthy ones are important building blocks to future family formation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Independent research of SRA programs confirms that this approach resonates with teens. In fact, about 25 behavioral studies demonstrate that students who are a part of SRA programs are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;    More likely to delay sex than their peers;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;    Have fewer partners and less sex if they become sexually active;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;    And are no less likely to use condoms than their peers. (Yes, SRA programs share medically accurate information about contraception and teens learn that while contraception may reduce some of the risks, only abstinence will prevent all the possible consequences of teen sex.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The CDC confirms that age of sexual initiation is an important predictor of long-term sexual health. A growing body of social science research correlates sexual delay to increasing the probability of other positive outcomes, including educational, emotional, and relational success. Only SRA programs provide adequate practical skills to increase sexual delay. So-called  “comprehensive” sex ed programs insist they do the same, but a quick review of the most popular curricula show their claims fall flat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Critics are quick to dismiss the SRA approach by repeating tired talking points, citing old, inaccurate, and ideologically-motivated “reports,” and defining the entire SRA field by predictably pointing to some outlier rogue program that is far out of the mainstream for our field. I hope that thoughtful citizens and professionals will refuse to be cowed by this intentional deception.  Instead, I hope they will focus on something much more important than winning a political debate – and that is on an entire generation of youth who deserve more than the soft bigotry of low expectations when it comes to their sexual health – and their future success.  I believe that when that becomes the focus – we will see agreement that SRA education MUST be given priority emphasis. And then the debate will no longer be IF the SRA message should be provided to youth, but HOW to assure that it is provided in the best and most relevant manner possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Valerie Huber is the President/CEO of the National Abstinence Education Association, a professional association in support of abstinence education as the optimal strategy for teen sexual health. Valerie previously served as the Title V Abstinence Education Coordinator for the state of Ohio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;U.S. Needs More Comprehensive Sex Education&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taryn Gal&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The effectiveness and importance of comprehensive sex education to reduce adolescent engagement in risky sexual behaviors is a non-negotiable fact, yet, for years, the United States has given billions in federal funding to abstinence-only until marriage programs.  Recently, exciting shifts in funding show that state and federal governments are also, largely, in support of comprehensive sex education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A history lacking in comprehensive sex education has resulted in a generation of youth without the knowledge and skills necessary to take responsibility for their bodies and health.  It should, therefore, not be surprising that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;     The US has the highest teen pregnancy rate among the world’s developed nations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;     46.8% of US high school students have had sex, including 64% of 12th graders[1]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;     Over 40% of US high school students did not use a condom the last time they had sex[2]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;     Only 14.7% of US high school students reported having ever been taught in school about AIDS or HIV infection[3]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;     Youth ages 15-24 make up just 27% of the sexually active population, yet account for 50% of the new sexually transmitted infections (STIs) in the US each year[4]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, there are multiple complicatedly connected factors influencing adolescent engagement in risky sexual behavior (e.g., parents, peers, romantic partner, culture), not simply what is taught in school.  For the purposes of this argument, however, we will focus primarily on the necessity of comprehensive sex education in school, as that is where we can have the greatest influence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take a minute and think back to your experience in sex ed as a teenager – if you had formal sex ed at all.  I bet it was far from satisfactory and left questions unanswered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you grew up in the United States, it’s likely you received subpar sex education.  According to the Guttmacher Institute[5], only 22 states and the District of Columbia require public schools to teach sex education and only 33 require instruction about HIV/AIDS.  Only 13 states require that sex education be medically accurate, only two prohibit the program from promoting religion, and just 18 states and the District of Columbia require information on contraception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Comprehensive sex education has been proven to be effective in delaying initiation of sex, reducing the frequency of sexual activity and number of sex partners, increasing condom and contraceptive use, and, thereby, reducing sexually transmitted infections.[6]  Comprehensive sex education does not, as opponents argue, increase sexual behaviors among youth or send mixed messages.  Experts, including the American Academy of Pediatrics, American Medical Association, World Health Organization, and American Public Health Association recommend comprehensive sex education programs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A comprehensive sex education must consist of replicating, with fidelity, evidence-based curricula containing factual and medically appropriate information on healthy relationships, decision-making, negotiation, body image, bullying, cybersafety, good touch/bad touch (sexual abuse), different kinds of family structures, gender roles, abortion, sexual orientation, STIs (including HPV vaccination), HIV/AIDS, contraception, abstinence, gender identity and expression, anatomy and physiology, puberty, and reproduction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to be truly effective, sex education must be communicated early and often in a comprehensive, ongoing, age-appropriate, honest, and open conversation.  In order to have a sexually healthy adolescence, open communication must begin long before the teenage years – when a child is old enough to be naming body parts, be sexual abused, have same-sex parents, or ask questions. It’s never too early to start the conversation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Opponents of comprehensive sex education are oftentimes proponents of abstinence only until marriage curricula.  Usually founded on moral beliefs, sex outside of a heterosexual monogamous marriage is framed as dangerous and shameful.  This outdated heteronormative approach has not only failed to produce sufficient evidence of effectiveness, but can be harmful to youth, as it does not provide the information necessary for adolescents to protect themselves and does not address the needs of lesbian, gay, bisexual, transgender, queer, or questioning youth.  Evidence has shown that “increasing emphasis on abstinence education is positively correlated with teenage pregnancy and birth rates.”[7]  It is astonishing, yet apparent, the powerful role religion, morals, values, fear, and discomfort play in censoring knowledge we provide to youth.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving forward, youth must be involved in the needs assessments and policy development pertaining to comprehensive sex education.  Youth voice is too often ignored or silenced.  As the Michigan Youth Advisory Council, coordinated by the Michigan Organization on Adolescent Sexual Health, says, “Nothing about us without us.”  Educators must be educated to provide comprehensive sex education.  This includes parents (parent-child communication about sex is perhaps the most influential factor in adolescent engagement in risky sexual behavior), physicians, and health teachers, to name a few. If the recent increase in federal funding for evidence-based comprehensive sex education is any indication, it appears that the US might be (slowly, but remarkably), heading in the right direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taryn Gal is the Outreach Coordinator at the Michigan Organization on Adolescent Sexual Health. She has worked in the field of sexual health promotion for over ten years, including development and implementation of comprehensive evidence-based sexual education programs.  She has her Master’s degree from the University of Michigan School of Public Health.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Guantanamo Bay: Practicing Our Values or Protecting Ourselves?</title>
      <link>http://consideronline.org/issues/2015-02-23-guantanamo-bay-practicing-our-values-or-protecting-ourselves/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2015 19:09:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consideronline.org/issues/2015-02-23-guantanamo-bay-practicing-our-values-or-protecting-ourselves/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;February 23, 2015
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;pro&#34;&gt;Pro&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Melvyn Levitsky&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is certainly a relevant question in the wake of the Senate Foreign Intelligence Committee’s recent release of its report on the CIA’s “enhanced interrogation techniques” (EITs).. Since the most onerous interrogation practices were terminated during the latter stages of the George W. Bush Administration and banned completely by the Obama Administration, we might assume that the question posed has already been answered. However, CIA Director Brennan in a recent news conference gave a vague response as to whether such techniques might ever be employed in the future. My comment on the question is that it is not “either-or.” I believe we can protect our values and ourselves in interrogating suspected or proven terrorists. Our law enforcement agencies have developed practices in interrogation that have had some success without such brutal techniques as water boarding, forced rectal hydration or chaining naked prisoners to the walls of their cells. The US Army Field Manual incorporates the same approach as the FBI and this, according to Brennan, has become the standard for CIA practices as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The use of torture is clearly contrary to American values embedded in our founding documents and in our democratic system. The case against torture is also a treaty obligation linked to our signature and ratification of the 1984 UN Convention against Torture. Treaty obligations are considered to be binding in terms of both domestic and international law and behavior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reportedly, the legal basis for the use of “enhanced interrogation techniques” was given in a late-2001 Justice Department memorandum employing the so-called “necessity defense.” The essence of this rather imprecise doctrine is that in some cases a technical breach of the law can be overcome by the advantage to society of the result of the breach. In the case of enhanced interrogation, this would mean that torturing prisoners could produce information that would protect American citizens by preventing acts of terrorism against them or by leading to the capture of people or groups planning such acts. The problem with this is that there is no clear evidence that torture has resulted in actionable intelligence that has led to prevention of a terrorist act or capture of a terrorist. In fact, during his news conference, Director Brennan stated, that the link between useful information and specific anti-terrorist actions undertaken by the United States, such as the killing of Osama bin Laden, was “unknowable.”  (If it were unquestionably otherwise, I might have a different view of the “necessity defense” to justify the use of certain EITs.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How does Guantanamo Bay fit into this issue? First let’s differentiate between Guantanamo Bay US Naval Base and Guantanamo Bay Detention Camp. The US has occupied the Naval Base (called “Gitmo”) in accordance with a US-Cuba treaty of the early twentieth century. The base itself can only be closed by mutual consent. In itself, it has no particular connection to anti-terrorist policy. The Detention Camp, located on the 45-square mile base, however, does. Since 2001 it has housed over 700 inmates, most of them captured during anti-terrorist operations in Afghanistan and other countries. Over 500 of these detainees, most of them formally uncharged, have been released or transferred to other countries. The Bush Administration considered the inmates to be “illegal combatants” and since the base was not on US territory, they could be denied certain American legal protections. The Administration also determined that the inmates should be tried by military tribunals. These positions have been amended somewhat by Supreme Court decisions, but the fact is that the remaining 150 prisoners, approximately 50 of which are considered to be hard-core terrorists (for example, the admitted mastermind of &lt;sup&gt;9&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;11&lt;/sub&gt;, Khalid Sheikh Mohammed) are being detained without trial. Some of them were subjected to “enhanced interrogation” before the practice was banned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Candidate Obama promised to close the Guantanamo camp, but acknowledged that it would be difficult to honor our commitment to the rule of law without “releasing people intent on blowing us up.”  An Executive Order he signed early in his administration was overridden by Congressional action. Congress denied funds for the transfer of prisoners or the building of facilities to hold them on US territory and made it clear that it would stand in the way of any attempt to close the Guantanamo camp. No further clarification of the future legal status of the detainees has been offered by the US Government. Until a political consensus can be reached as to what to do with the remaining detainees, there is no prospect – nor no particular argument – for closing down the camp. It’s too early to say whether resumption of full diplomatic relations with Cuba will change this equation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ambassador (ret) Melvyn Levitsky is Professor of International Policy and Practice at U of M&amp;rsquo;s Gerald Ford School of Public Policy. He teaches courses in international relations. During his 35­ year career as a US Foreign Service Officer he served as Ambassador to Bulgaria and Brazil, a Executive Secretary of the State Department and as an Assistant Secretary of State.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;title-a-history-of-false-narratives&#34;&gt;Title: A History of False Narratives&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt; Shayana Kadidal&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;President Obama’s first major speech on national security stated that, “instead of serving as a tool to counter terrorism, Guantánamo became a symbol that helped al Qaeda recruit terrorists to its cause.  Indeed, … Guantánamo likely created more terrorists around the world than it ever detained.” John McCain and President Bush agreed throughout the 2008 campaign. Bipartisan consensus ran throughout government; the Senate Armed Services Committee, in a unanimous report on the treatment of detainees in U.S. custody, quoted Navy General Counsel Alberto Mora: “the first and second identifiable causes of U.S. combat deaths in Iraq - as judged by their effectiveness in recruiting insurgent fighters into combat - are, respectively the symbols of Abu Ghraib and Guantánamo.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, as ISIS dresses its victims in Guantánamo-orange jumpsuits, these concerns remain as serious as they were six years ago. Yet bipartisan support for the closure of Guantánamo has eroded; even former POW McCain supports an amendment to effectively block any releases from a prison where all but ten men remain detained without any charges against them. What happened?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the first month of Obama’s presidency, the Defense Information Agency has issued leaks to the press claiming absurdly high numbers of released detainees have engaged in “recidivism” – a “return” to terrorism or just “anti-American activity” after release. (Ironic quotation marks are necessary since just a tiny handful of the released were ever charged with offenses in the first place.) These claims almost entirely fail to name names or specify allegations (perhaps because the first few men named were accused of complaining to the &lt;em&gt;New York Times&lt;/em&gt; about their abuse in Gtmo). Given where most men were sent back to – quasi-failed states like Afghanistan, police states like Saudi Arabia – the claims would be unverifiable even if the military did name names, since in many ways those countries are as much of a black box as Gtmo itself was in its initial days. And given the aggressive recruitment of intelligence cooperators from the ranks of prisoners, it makes sense that the Defense Department would claim high numbers of releases had returned to terrorism, as that narrative provides cover for former detainees attempting to work their way into insurgent organizations on behalf of our government. We at CCR have been unable to identify even a half-dozen actual “recidivism” cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, this overblown fear has created logistical roadblocks to releasing even men cleared by the task force Obama created in 2009 to review each prisoner’s case. To be cleared required the unanimous consent of the CIA, FBI, the military, and Justice and State Departments. But even men who have crossed that high a threshold will not be released without assurances from the receiving country that they will be subject to constant monitoring and international travel bans. That has slowed the pace of transfers for the cleared men , 87% of whom are Yemenis now destined for resettlement in third countries, but the task is manageable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, to actually finish the job will require dealing with two groups of men not cleared by the Task Force. The first is the small group of men (under three dozen) the task force designated for prosecution. Congress has forced all these cases into the military commissions system. Even after two radical overhauls of that system in 2006 and 2009, today only seven defendants have active cases, mired in the perpetual delay endemic to complex novel organizations.  At this point, anyone who believes this dysfunctional system deserves to try the &lt;sup&gt;9&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;11&lt;/sub&gt; case or any other is not genuinely interested in seeing justice ever delivered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final group consists of 35 men neither cleared nor expected to be charged. Thanks to WikiLeaks, we now know that even on the military’s account there is little to distinguish many of these men from the cleared pool, and indeed, of the nine of these men recently re-reviewed by military PRB panels, six have been cleared for transfer. For a long time people claimed Gtmo was full of men “too dangerous to release, but impossible to try,” presumptively because interrogators had contaminated otherwise-accurate evidence against them through use of torture. The notion that torture renders men at Gtmo untriable is laughable to any federal prosecutor – the usual remedy is to bring lesser charges that can be proved without using anyone’s past coerced confession. One example: attendance at a training camp – an allegation flung at nearly every Gtmo detainee at some point in the past – presumably was witnessed by thousands. Not all were tortured, or unwilling now to testify. The reality is that the “forever prisoners” are people the government never had any intent to charge – they are better described as “awaiting clearance” than “too dangerous to release.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, the iron curtain of secrecy that still remains in place around everything at Guantánamo conceals all of these ugly realities from public scrutiny. By January 2016 – less than a year from now – Guantanamo will have been open under a Democratic president longer than it was under President Bush. The anomaly has quietly become the new normal. We will – less quietly – continue to pay a price for that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shayana Kadidal is senior managing attorney of the Guantanamo Global Justice Initiative at the Center for Constitutional Rights in New York City. He is a 1994 graduate of Yale Law School and a former law clerk to Judge Kermit Lipez of the United States Court of Appeals for the First Circuit. In his twelve years at the Center, he has worked on a number of significant cases arising in the wake of &lt;sup&gt;9&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;11&lt;/sub&gt;, including the Center&amp;rsquo;s challenges to the detention of prisoners at Guantánamo Bay (among) them torture victim Mohammed al Qahtani and former CIA ghost detainee Majid Khan), which have twice reached the Supreme Court, and several cases arising out of the post­9/11 domestic immigration sweeps. He was also counsel in CCR&amp;rsquo;s legal challenges to the &amp;ldquo;material support&amp;rdquo; statute (Holder v.Humanitarian Law Project, decided by the Supreme Court in 2010), to the low rates of black firefighter hiring in New York City, and to the NSA&amp;rsquo;s warrantless surveillance program. Along with others at the Center, he currently serves as U.S. counsel to WikiLeaks publisher Julian Assange. On behalf of plaintiffs including Assange, Glenn Greenwald, and other journalists, he led litigation that ultimately resulted in public release of over 550 previously­withheld documents during the court­martial of Pvt. Bradley (now Chelsea) Manning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Net Neutrality</title>
      <link>http://consideronline.org/issues/2015-02-05-net-neutrality-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2015 19:09:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consideronline.org/issues/2015-02-05-net-neutrality-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;February 5, 2015
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;net-neutrality-unfairly-limits-business-models&#34;&gt;Net Neutrality Unfairly Limits Business Models&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jeffrey Dorfman&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With President Obama’s urging, the Federal Communication Commission (a technically independent government agency) appears nearly ready to issue a set of net neutrality rules that he favors. Many individual internet users and businesses whose business models rely on equal internet access for all are also lobbying the FCC for their preferred solution. However, net neutrality is not as good an idea or as neutral a concept as many people believe. Rather, it is another attempt at government control and enforced equality in a realm where that makes little sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Net neutrality seems like a simple concept: the company that links your computer/tablet/smartphone to the internet should not be able to discriminate among users and providers in the level of connectivity service provided. That is, we should all be able to send and receive the same number of bits of data per second. Another way to think about it is that net neutrality is a like a public highway that everyone has equal access to drive on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a bad idea for the same reason that only having vanilla ice cream for sale is a bad idea: some people want, and are willing to pay for, something different. Forcing a one-size-fits-all solution on the Internet stifles innovation by blocking some companies from turning new ideas or business models into successful products. Innovation drives economic growth, variety increases consumer welfare; net neutrality would reduce both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;President Obama was quoted in his statement saying that “We cannot allow Internet service providers (ISPs) to restrict the best access or to pick winners and losers in the online marketplace for services and ideas.” Yet, enforcing net neutrality is picking winners and losers even if it looks like it is just “leveling the playing field.” Net neutrality would completely block certain business models and stop any possible innovation that might emerge if given the option of seeking differential access to bandwidth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key point that President Obama and all the supporters of net neutrality have missed is that ISPs and the companies that control the Internet backbone infrastructure that knits everything together do not have the power to pick winners and losers either. Consumers decide what products and services are successful because we adopt them. If an ISP blocks Netflix because of the bandwidth it requires, consumers who want Netflix will take their business elsewhere. If enough people do so, the ISP will have to change policies or go out of business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alternatively, if Netflix wants to pay internet service providers (including the backbone companies) to receive priority delivery of its packets of information, they should be allowed to and it will become Netflix’s problem to charge customers enough to cover that additional business expense. After all, a “non-neutral” internet will charge for better service and if we consumers do not find that worth our money, companies using that business model will fail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the former chief economist for the FCC, Thomas Hazlett, pointed out recently in &lt;em&gt;Time&lt;/em&gt;, Facebook, Instagram, Twitter, LinkedIn (and many, many more success stories of innovation) all emerged without the benefit of net neutrality. In the time when the government might have been ensuring a level playing field for the Internet pipe into our homes, smartphones and mobile devices completely changed how most people connect to and use the Internet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem with government regulation of the Internet is that by the time the government studies how it works and what is needed, technology has moved on. Who believes that the government can write a regulation that will still fit the bill in three years when none of us know what the dominant formats, companies, and technology will be by then? Given that the FCC has been proposing net neutrality rules for a decade with little success, why would we expect a change anytime soon?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More choices are good for consumers. We benefit from the large variety of cars available for purchase. The fact that most people cannot afford some of those models does not mean they should be removed from sale. Similarly, the fact that some businesses or consumers may choose to pay for better access to the Internet is not a bad thing. Some people pay more to fly first class, but they do not interfere with my travel in coach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As long as the government enforces the antitrust laws and ensures that consumers can choose among methods and providers for how they connect to the Internet, consumers can pick winners and losers by voting with their time, their eyeballs, and their dollars. No government needed, thank you very much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jeffrey Dorfman is a professor of applied economics at The University of Georgia where he teaches economic theory and food industry economics and management. His research spans virtually all facets of economics, focusing on empirical policy analysis. He is a regular contributor of opinion columns to Forbes.com and RealClearMarkets.com.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-internet-needs-a-network-neutrality-principle&#34;&gt;The Internet Needs a Network Neutrality Principle&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Faith Sparr&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nation has been engaging in this network neutrality debate for well over a decade.  In that time, interest in the conversation has waxed and waned, but it has reached a fever pitch over the last year or so.  The increased attention began last May when the FCC issued its proposed rulemaking on Protecting and Promoting an Open Internet and continued through last summer when John Oliver addressed the issue in a June episode of his Last Week Tonight show.  So what is all this fuss about anyway?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing that John Oliver got exactly right is that a lot of folks will try to make this issue sound incredibly complicated so that citizens will simply stop paying attention.  When citizens stop paying attention that creates a vacuum for other interested parties to write the rules for the Internet.  Those interested parties are likely to be large cable and telecommunications companies.  But don’t believe it.  In reality, the issue isn’t all that complicated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic idea of network neutrality rests on a long-standing Internet principle called the end-to-end principle. Based on this principle, what ends up being transformative about the Internet is what runs on top of it (the content, the applications, etc.)  It’s not the fiber optic cables, coaxial cables, or copper wires; it is what resides on the ends of the network that makes the difference.  What most proponents of network neutrality would like to see is a rule that prohibits Internet Service Providers (ISPs) (the owners of those cables and wires which reach your home) from discriminating against, blocking, slowing down, or otherwise interfering with the content you are trying to access on the Internet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;       &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seems simple, right?  Well, here is some of what you will hear from network neutrality opponents:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt; _The Internet is fine.  Leave it alone.  Look how it has blossomed so far without network neutrality. _&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again—don’t believe it.  The fact is the FCC, through various rulings in the 1980s and 1990s, had been imposing regulations on the transmission side of the Internet up until 2002.  In 2002 the FCC reclassified both the transmission side of Internet service and any additional bundled services offered by ISPs as “information services”.  The reclassification meant that the FCC’s power in regulating ISPs was greatly diminished.  However, soon after the reclassification, the FCC wrote some basic Internet freedoms into policy, and later made those guidelines more permanent in its 2010 Open Internet Order (which Verizon later challenged in court as being beyond the FCC’s invoked authority—Verizon won that suit).  The early “freedoms” and subsequent order included language in the general vein of a neutrality principle.  In short, the neutrality principle has been much more the rule rather than the exception throughout the Internet’s rapid growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt; &lt;em&gt;This is about consumer choice.  If your ISP is blocking or slowing down content you want—find another provider.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one reminds me of a South Park episode when the adults go down to the cable company and complain that the kids have placed a parental lock on their cable channels.  The cable representative tells the adults that if they don’t like the cable company’s policies they can find another cable company—then the rep sarcastically adds, “oh, there’s not another cable company, is there?”.  A recent NTIA report shows that 82% of consumers have just one option for reasonably fast broadband service.  That’s not what I’d call choice.  Not to mention that the so-called choice proponents have been working hard to restrict municipalities from providing high speed wi-fi to their citizens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt; &lt;em&gt;But Netflix is a broadband hog and it should pay to deliver content to our customers&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an interesting argument; it also depends on how you view what happens when a customer requests Netflix’s (or any other content provider’s) content.  Is the customer using the ISPs’ bandwidth or is it the content provider?  After all, isn’t this the beauty of the Internet?  Netflix comes along and disrupts other companies’ business models (say the cable companies’) and becomes extremely popular in the process.   Down the road another streaming service bests Netflix.  Do we want our ISP to be the gatekeeper for the next big application or service?  If the ISP wants to charge me more because I want faster speeds, fine.  This is already the business model.  But what I don’t want are deals on the other side of the transmission that I don’t have sight to and which means one website, one application, one service might be loading more quickly and therefore becomes the next “winner” on the Internet stage.  Not because that site/app/service is the best, but because it paid the fee to the ISP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John Oliver was on to something last summer when he noted that if you want to do something “evil” (Oliver’s words) hide it in something boring.  So as you hear the words “common carrier”, “Title II”, “forbearance”, “tariff” and the like, keep your eye on the ball.  What the Internet will look like in the future depends on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Faith Sparr teaches in the Department of Communication Studies at the University of Michigan. Prior to teaching, she served as in-house counsel for Sprint. Her research includes analysis of the FCC&amp;rsquo;s regulation of indecency, free speech and public events and public spaces on the Internet.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Legalize Our Campus?</title>
      <link>http://consideronline.org/issues/2016-02-10-legalize-our-campus/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2015 19:09:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consideronline.org/issues/2016-02-10-legalize-our-campus/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;February 3, 2015
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;legal-pot-it-s-good-for-you&#34;&gt;Legal Pot? It&amp;rsquo;s Good For You.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;by Erin Dunne&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fervor about legal marijuana is sweeping the nation. Presidential candidates have voiced their concerns and their intentions. Some states have legalized medical marijuana and others have even approved it for recreational use. On college campuses across the country, however, marijuana – medical and recreational – remains illegal regardless of state laws.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Virtually every college or university depends on federal funding. That federal funding comes with restrictions and, of course, adherence to federal drug laws. Without a change in federal legislation, college campuses will remain as they are, regardless of state law or local ordinances. It is for this reason that here in Ann Arbor a stop for marijuana could lead either to a fine on city property (local ordinance) or, just a few blocks away on university property, handcuffs and a misdemeanor (federal law).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking a step back, then, to answer what the effects of legalization would be for a college campus depends on where and how legalization happens. If it happens at the state level, almost nothing will change for students at the University of Michigan who would still be arrested, fingerprinted and brought to court for use anywhere on university property. If legalized at the federal level, however, those restrictions would change. Instead of criminal penalties, the University’s own policies, such as mandatory classes, would be the only official consequences. Here, it is also important to consider that most current legalization efforts explicitly state that legal recreational use would be restricted to those over the age of 21. As many college students are not yet 21, those individuals would still be subject to legal consequences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Legal marijuana is about much more than college students facing arrest or a fine. The traditional arguments of legalization still ring true. The war on drugs following marijuana becoming illegal has disproportionately affected poor, often minority communities. Those who are arrested for marijuana are often left with a criminal record and/or punitive probation terms that can later contribute to harsher sentencing. Marijuana has documented medicinal uses and keeping it illegal denies those in need of medication. Marijuana is no more dangerous or addictive than cigarettes or alcohol. Keeping marijuana illegal is an infringement on individual rights. The war on drugs simply costs too much; legal marijuana would provide much needed tax revenue. Prohibition doesn’t work. The list seems endless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, these reasons seem abstract or distant to many college students. Taking a selfish and pragmatic approach and looking at the benefits of legalization for college students seems necessary. First and foremost, college students would be safer. On an academic level, universities would be able to pursue interesting and lucrative cannabis related research. From an educational standpoint, students would have access to course work that would prepare them to compete in the newly legal and clearly profitable world of cannabis and hemp production, distribution, and marketing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Current federally mandated draconian drug laws enforced on college campuses and in university housing cause more harm than good to the very population they claim to protect.  Students face harsh penalties for violations of policies and consequently fear seeking medical attention. Students have few sources of accurate information and if caught, must deal with costly academic and professional repercussions. Students who receive financial aid lose their eligibility for a misdemeanor conviction. Victims of sexual assault seeking care protected under medical amnesty policies for alcohol use still face prosecution for drug use. Moreover, even those students with approval from a physician for state legalized medical marijuana are denied access on campus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a schedule 1 controlled substance, widespread bans on research and academic exploration into the properties of cannabis remain stringently controlled - especially in university-sponsored laboratories. The research potential of both hemp and cannabis are enormous and promise to be lucrative in terms of both patents and industry application.  Furthermore, at a school like the University of Michigan, with a dedication to medical research, the possibilities of medical marijuana as a treatment method could yield fruitful results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, as job markets become ever more competitive, it is important to leave college with skills applicable to emerging markets and fields. Legal medical and recreational marijuana create new industry related jobs that very few individuals are currently qualified to do. Legal marijuana would also open possibilities for new classes and entrepreneurial learning opportunities to jumpstart industry related careers of students after graduation. Cutting edge business courses in understanding new laws, marketing courses, and even research opportunities could all be available to students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, legal marijuana on college campus would have little impact unless it comes from the federal level. If legalized federally, colleges would only gain from legal medical and recreational marijuana. Students would have a safer college experience, and new research opportunities would emerge. Directly applicable skills-based course work could help students secure jobs in emerging fields. Even for those who do not support traditional arguments in favor of legalization, pragmatic applications of legalization bear obvious benefits to the University of Michigan community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Erin&lt;/strong&gt; is a current LS&amp;amp;A junior studying History and International Studies. When not delving into the past, Erin is busy serving as the Co-Director of Students for Sensible Drug Policy on campus and working as a DJ at WCBN. Tune into her radio show to hear both bluegrass and overly personal stories broadcast over the airwaves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;not-so-harmless-after-all&#34;&gt;Not So Harmless After All&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;by Joshua Meisler, LLMSW, M.Ed&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;       
Let us first review the most powerful pro-legalization arguments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “War on Drugs” is a failure by any measure.  Nationally, we incarcerate our citizens at one of the highest rates in the world, and a huge percentage of adjudicated people in this country are being punished for non-violent drug related offenses, many of which involve marijuana.  Prevention, education, and treatment services are chronically underfunded and culturally and politically marginalized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most destructive features of our failed drug war is the disproportionate impact of our punitive regime on historically under resourced populations, particularly African American, Hispanic, and First Nations people.   Those populations are prosecuted, convicted, and incarcerated at disproportionate rates across the criminal justice system, and especially in terms of drug related offenses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although these phenomena are apparent on the county and state level, there is no data to suggest that they extend to the campus community at University of Michigan.  Although the families and loved ones of members of the campus community may be affected by these conditions, there is very a low level of enforcement of marijuana related offenses across campus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, the strongest arguments in favor of legalization are essentially irrelevant when considering the campus community’s well-being.                                                                                                                                     &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In contrast, emerging neuroscience and public health data reveal that Marijuana is anything but “harmless”, especially for college aged people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of Neuroscience, a revolution in our ability to study the brain and how it works is well underway.  We have more precise information than ever before regarding brain development.  One of the most important things we have learned is that brain development continues through the early- to mid- twenties, an age range that includes the majority of our student body.   During this crucial final phase of development, connections are formed and solidified between the frontal lobe, which is the site of critical thinking, cause and effect, and other adult mental processes, and the parts of the brain which regulate pleasure, impulsivity, and risk taking.  Research has clearly demonstrated that the introduction of marijuana seriously retards and may prevent completion of these essential developmental tasks, leading to long term negative consequences and outcomes for adolescent and young adult users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also data which indicates that regular marijuana use through adolescence and early adulthood is linked to a 10-12 point lower IQ score as compared to non-users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, it has long been generally accepted that marijuana use interferes with short term memory, information retention, and focus.  It seems counter intuitive that we would endorse a substance that is so detrimental to the skills and behaviors necessary to meet the goals of higher education at our world class institution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the Public Health perspective, experts assert that social and cultural messaging has a strong impact upon using patterns.  It is concerning that the information about the harms of marijuana use in adolescence and early adulthood are so little known in the general public and among University of Michigan communities in particular.  Legalization would send a dangerous message to the vulnerable and already under informed student population.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our current politics and policies regarding marijuana use are not working.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are in dire need of rigorous public information and education campaigns to insure that potential marijuana users are thoroughly and accurately informed when they are deciding whether or not to use the drug.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We desperately need to invest in treatment and recovery resources.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of the campus community specifically, changes in policy and resource allocation to encourage and facilitate the admission of potential students with drug related criminal history, and to develop and sustain campus culture and communities, which support recovery, would go a long way towards improving the University response to the negative impact of substance use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Legalization addresses none of these shortcomings in our drug policy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the whole, the campus community is not affected by the negative consequences of the criminalization of marijuana.  We are, however, particularly vulnerable to the negative outcomes associated with adolescent and early adult use of marijuana.  Legalization will have an overall detrimental impact on the health, wellbeing, and academic and intellectual success of the campus community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Joshua&lt;/strong&gt; holds undergraduate and graduate degrees from University of Michigan.  He is a social worker and educator who grew up in Ann Arbor, and has preserved his vintage $5.00 possession ticket as proof.  He currently provides clinical services to adjudicated youth in Washtenaw County for the non-profit organization Growth Works, Inc.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>